<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The doctrine of faith, justification and assurance humbly endeavoured to be farther cleared towards the satisfaction and comfort of all free unbiassed spirits, with appendix for peace / by Robert Dixon, prebendary of Rochester.</title>
            <author>Dixon, Robert, d. 1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 190 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36184</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1747</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32761</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12753509</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12753509</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93356</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36184)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93356)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1526:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The doctrine of faith, justification and assurance humbly endeavoured to be farther cleared towards the satisfaction and comfort of all free unbiassed spirits, with appendix for peace / by Robert Dixon, prebendary of Rochester.</title>
                  <author>Dixon, Robert, d. 1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 112 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Godbid,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.LXVIII [1668]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faith.</term>
               <term>Justification.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93356:1"/>
            <p>THE DOCTRINE OF FAITH, JUSTIFICATION, <hi>AND</hi> ASSURANCE, <hi>Humbly Endeavoured to be farther cleared towards the ſatisfaction and comfort of all free <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbiaſſed Spirits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With an APPENDIX for <hi>PEACE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY <hi>ROBERT DIXON,</hi> Prebendary of ROCHESTER.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 12.31.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Covet after the beſt gifts, and yet I ſhew you a more excellent way.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>William Godbid.</hi> M.DC.LXVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:93356:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93356:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> EDWARD HALES, <hi>Baronet.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD is the great Maker and beſtower of all Rights: The perſons capable to receive them, and to whom he doth convey them, are Angels and Men. To mankind he gives the beſt of Rights, and inveſts them with the beſt Inheritance, by the beſt Mediator Jeſus Chriſt, the Principal Heir of all Things, through the means of Faith, which juſtifies the Sons of Men by Nature, to be the beſt Title, and the ſtrongeſt Aſſurance that can be had to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93356:3"/>
            <p>I have therefore purpoſely fixed upon theſe noble Principles of <hi>Faith, Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> That I might be a true <hi>Mercury</hi> to point out the ſtately way that leads to Coeleſtial Glory. Directing wiſe Souls to come off from the wandring Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits of earthly Pomps, empty Speculations, and uncertain Riches, which diſcompoſe and tyre the beſt Wits in the Labyrinth of this World: That they may find true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in the Choice of that one Thing which is truly neceſſary, That better part which ſhall never be taken from them; That ſolid comfort which will ſtand by them, and bring them Peace to the end, and in the end, and unto all Eternity.</p>
            <p>This pain Treatiſe of theſe moſt high and moſt Chriſtian Truths, I held my ſelf obliged to dedicate unto you, as being the firſt Fruits of my Labours in this kind, and therefore moſt due to you of all men, who was my firſt Benefactor and moſt liberal Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron of my Studies, together with your moſt excellent Lady, now with God.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93356:3"/>
            <p>Her tranſcendent Eſtate I cannot reach, but Yours, and both your Sons I may, and do Addreſs my ſelf unto. And for the joynt-favours which I have received from you and your Lady during your conjugal Union, and for your continued and for her ſake increaſed kindneſs ſince the ſad ſeparation, I humbly offer this token of my Gratitude to remain by you, from me, to look into upon occaſions for your Satisfaction and comfort, in the midſt of the Diſ-ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions and Diſcomforts of this Miſerable World.</p>
            <p>The ſame alſo I deſire you would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to your Sons, the Stems of that Noble Lady, whoſe memory I ſhall ever honour, and you and them for her ſake.</p>
            <p>In this I aime meerly to ſtrike the ſprightly veine of Pure Love to You and to your hopeful Family, and a deer Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance and kindneſs to you all, as to the beſt of my Friends.</p>
            <p>Upon which generous Terms if you pleaſe to accept of this ſmall Preſent it may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote
<pb facs="tcp:93356:4"/>the acceptation thereof to others, and encourage him farther, who ever deſires to ſhew himſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt faithful, and moſt affectionate Servant <hi>ROBERT DIXON.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Rocheſter. <date>
                     <hi>March.</hi> 26. 1668.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:93356:4"/>
            <head>To the honeſt READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>AITH is all in all to a Chriſtian; For all that have Faith, are thereby Juſtified, and have full Right to all the Promiſes of God, To be his Sons by Adoption and Grace, to have their Sins pardoned, to be Sanctified by the Holy Spirit, and thereby to have all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Aſſiſtance and comfortable Aſſurance of a Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Inheritance of Eternal Life. I therefore pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely wave all perplexed Diſputes, and ſubtil Notions and Diſtinctions, which ſerve for nothing but to puzzle all men, eſpeciall them that are weak in the Faith. It ſhall ſuffice all Chriſtians, if they are willing to embrace Gods Promiſes, and perform his Precepts with an honeſt heart. Let them not trouble themſelves at all with the variety of Sects and Factions. For all ſuch true hearted and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Souls, do belong to Chriſt his Church, what ever Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences there be in Opinions cauſed by vain men who do not underſtand one another, being ſore blinded with Pride and idle Speculations which engender nothing but Strife and Diviſions. Keep thou therefore, Good Reader, Faith and a good Conſcience, and paſs not for the raſh Cenſures of any. Be thou confident of Gods un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable favour, if thou be no Hypocrite. In Order therefore to the ſatisfaction and comfort of tender Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, I have written this ſhort Treatiſe, and do encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them to do their true endeavour to pleaſe God, and
<pb facs="tcp:93356:5"/>to perſerverance, and truſt in him for the certainty of their future eſtate of Happineſs and Salvation, which he hath undoubtedly provided for them. Accept there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, kind Reader, what I have here offered; and then if God permit, I will add more to the ſame purpoſe: Avoiding all Nicety and Superfluity of Words, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcending in the great Points of Grace, Faith, Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and Aſſurance, to the meaneſt capacity; aiming at no Side, or Party, but equally reſpecting the plain Truth, with an unbiaſſed mind for Peace. This even Temper of Spirit, is the only means among all good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, eſpecially Divines, for the ſtinting of Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies in all fooliſh and unlearned Queſtions, and the Propagation of Piety, Peace and Love, in Church and State. This Rare Character of a True Child of God, to be pure and peaceable by obedience to good Laws and fulfilling all Righteouſneſs, is the ſafe way to Heaven. Thus we work out our Salvation with fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, and make our Calling and Election ſure; Which ſhall be the daily prayer of him, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the Lord Jeſus</hi> Robert Dixon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93356:5"/>
            <head>The Doctrine of FAITH, JUSTIFI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CATION and ASSURANCE.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>HEBR: 11.1.</hi> Now Faith is the Subſtance of things hoped for, the Evidence of things not ſeen.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>COHERENCE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Author having in the end of the former <hi>Chapter</hi> ſpoken of Faith, makes a digreſſion upon that occaſion to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain the Nature of Faith more larg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and produceth many examples of faithful men to provoke the <hi>Hebrews</hi> to imitate their Fathers and others in the Holy Faith, and thereby to endure afflictions, and to overcome them by Faith, as they had done.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:93356:6"/>
                  <head>EXPLICATION.</head>
                  <p>Theſe words are no Definition of Faith,<note place="margin">Chap. 1. <hi>Of</hi> Faith.</note> no more than thoſe, <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.29. where God is called <hi>A con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming Fire,</hi> are the Definition of God.</p>
                  <p>FAITH is a Thing Indefinite, and is not define<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, becauſe it is ſo general a Thing, that no Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius will comprehend it; yet it may be deſigned, a high Eſteem of Gods Exiſtence, Power, and Goodneſs. Beſides, definitions are dangerous; if in the Civil, much more in the Divine Law.</p>
                  <p>Two Notions are here laid down, as Principles and Elements, to conclude, that Faith was in thoſe perſons hereafter mentioned.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>The Subſtance of Things hoped for,</hi> is <hi>Faith.</hi> 1. Where Things hoped for do ſubſiſt, there is Faith; or where Things to come are preſent, there is Faith.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>The Evidence of Things not ſeen,</hi> is <hi>Faith;</hi> or where there is a ſight of Things not ſeen, there is Faith.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Principles are taken from the Object of Faith, Good Things to come, and therefore abſent and unſeen: But when the Soul apprehends them as preſent and viſible, then ſhe believes and hopes — <hi>For hope that is ſeen is not hope:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.24, 25.</note> 
                     <hi>for what a man ſeeth, why doth he yet hope for? But if we hope for that we ſee not, then do we with patience wait for it.</hi> A great Argument to Patience, by having an Eye to the Recompence of the Reward, and to the Price of the high Calling, which is layd up for us
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93356:6"/>in Chriſt, which cauſeth us to endure the Croſſe, and deſpiſe the Shame.</p>
                  <p>A great Argument to live by Faith, as if the Things were ſenſibly preſent, and ſeen; yea, by Faith they are made preſent, and ſeen; for <hi>Faith is the ſubſtance of things hoped for, and the evidence of Things not ſeen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Where therefore theſe Two Principles and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments are, they do neceſſarily inferre true Faith; and they do ſhew the excellency thereof, by the great effects of Patience and Courage, which were wrought in the hearts of thoſe famous Worthies, whereby they obtained ſo good a Report from God, who highly favoured them, and rewarded them for all their ſufferings.</p>
                  <p>The ſeveral Inſtances are very remarkable.<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>2.</hi> of Examples of <hi>Faith.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ver.</hi> 3.</note> The World framed by Gods Word, Things ſeen, made of Things that do not appear, but are underſtood by Faith.</p>
                  <p>By the Things now ſeen, we have a ſight of things unſeen, done long before our times. The Scripture makes Faith of it—<hi>Let there be light:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 33.6.</note> 
                     <hi>and there was light,</hi> &amp;c. —<hi>By the Word of the Lord were the Heavens made,</hi> &amp;c. He ſpake the word, and it was done.</p>
                  <p>We now ſee Trees of Trees, Living Creatures from Living Creatures, Men from Men; but theſe firſt Trees, Creatures and Men, had not their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning from theſe we now ſee,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 11.17.</note> but from the Chaos or Deep without Form.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ver.</hi> 4.</note> 
                     <hi>Abel</hi> offered a more excellent Sacrifice than
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93356:7"/>
                     <hi>Cain</hi> by Faith, (he leaves out <hi>Adam</hi> for his Sin) <hi>Abels</hi> Sacrifice was not more valuable than <hi>Cains,</hi> but more acceptable for his Faith. The other was, the Sacrifice of a Fool, <hi>i.e.</hi> a ſinner, this of a wiſe man, <hi>i. e.</hi> juſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Enoch</hi> was tranſlated by Faith,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.21.</note> for he walked with God, and ſo pleaſed God; how, but by Faith? <hi>for without Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Noah</hi> prepared an Arke by Faith, <hi>i. e.</hi> in hope of Gods promiſes. He had a ſight of Things unſeen, <hi>i.e.</hi> of the Floud yet to come, a Subſiſtence of Things hoped for, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſafely from the Univerſal Deluge.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8.</note> 
                     <hi>Abraham</hi> ſojourned and looked for a City to come by Faith, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 27.</note> and offered up <hi>Iſaac</hi> the Child of Faith in the Promiſe, not Nature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 11.</note> 
                     <hi>Sarah</hi> by Faith conceived in her old Age, above the ſtrength of Nature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 20.</note> 
                     <hi>Iſaac</hi> bleſſed <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> concerning things to come in the Promiſed Land.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 21.</note> 
                     <hi>Jacob</hi> dying in Faith and worſhipping, bleſſed his Sons to the Promiſed Land.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 22.</note> 
                     <hi>Joſeph</hi> by Faith gave Commandement concerning his bones to be buried in <hi>Canaan.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 23.</note> 
                     <hi>Moſes</hi> by Faith was ſaved from drowning, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to be called the Son of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Daughter; chooſing rather to ſuffer affliction with the People of God, than to enjoy the Pleaſure of ſin for a ſeaſon.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 30.</note> The Walls of <hi>Jericho</hi> fell down by Faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 31.</note> 
                     <hi>Rahab</hi> by Faith periſhed not with the Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:93356:7"/>
                  <p>So <hi>Gideon, Barak, Sampſon, Jephthah,</hi> and <hi>David, Samuel,</hi> and the Prophets; who by Faith ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Kingdoms, and wrought Righteouſneſs, obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Promiſes, endured tortures, ſtopped the mouths of Lyons, quenched the violence of Fire, waxed valiant in fight,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Mace:</hi>
                     </note> women received their dead raiſed to life again, <hi>&amp;c. Heb.</hi> 11.35.</p>
                  <p>All this Faith aroſe not from any cleer Promiſe of a Reſurrection,<note place="margin">Chap. <hi>3.</hi> Acts of Faith.</note> but hoping in Gods Power and Goodneſs, beyond this Life they endured all things here patiently: Much more may we that have a full and open Promiſe, and Example of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, by him that firſt brought Life and Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality to light through the Goſpel, and is the firſt born from the Dead, and the firſt fruits of them that ſlept.</p>
                  <p>Thus the Things that are abſent from us, and do ſubſiſt in themſelves, are made to ſubſiſt to us by our Faith. As Chriſts Birth, Life, Miracles, Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, Death, Reſurrection, Aſcenſion, Glory, all real in themſelves, ſubſiſting, though before our times, yet are made preſent by Faith: So our Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Aſcenſion, and Glory Eternal, not yet come nor ſeen, but are made preſent, and viſible by Faith, anticipating their being to us, before they be: For we live by Faith here, and not by Senſe. And bleſſed are thoſe that have ſeen Chriſt in the Fleſh, and the works that he did, and heard his words; yea, but much rather bleſſed are they, that have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeen, nor heard him, or his Works or Doctrine, and yet have believed.</p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:93356:8"/>
                  <p>And this is truly to know Chriſt, and by this knowledg of Faith, Chriſt is in us, and we in Chriſt. For we know not Chriſt now after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit, <hi>i.e.</hi> as he is ſpiritually preſent with us by Faith, and will be eternally preſent with us by ſight. For although we had lived in his time, and known him after the fleſh, or been his Natural Mother, Siſters, or Brethren; yet from henceforth by our Faith, we ſhould have known him no more in that ſtate of weakneſs and Mortality of Fleſh, but in a farre better ſtate of Eternal Glory and Power in the Spirit. And in the Union and Communion with him by Faith. And ſo we do know him, and by the hearing and believing of his Word, we are made one with him and he with us; are fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone; are his ſpiritual Mother, Siſters, and Brethren. Having fellowſhip alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy with the Father, and with the Son, by the Spirit of the Father and the Son, and are already in heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus; <hi>For Faith is the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of things hoped for, and the Evidence of things not ſeen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Subject of this Text, is <hi>Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Circumſtances are two:
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>The Subſtance of things hoped for.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <note place="margin">Chap. <hi>4.</hi> Of the fruits of Faith.</note> 
                           <hi>The Evidence of things not ſeen.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Reaſon is, Becauſe Faith obtains a preſent Right to a future Bleſſing, and an earneſt and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance thereof, and an Expectation of the full Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion.</p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:93356:8"/>
                  <p n="4">4. The Reaſon of this Reaſon, is from the Nature of Faith, which is not only an Aſſent to the Truth of Gods Promiſes, with a Reliance and Dependency upon God for the performance of them, but an acceptation and embracing them upon the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Holineſs, that they are offered unto us; which Faith is therefore accounted unto us for Righteouſneſs. That is, whereby we have a true Right, Intereſt, Title and Claim to the Inheritance of the Kingdom of Heaven, which is the Thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed unto us.</p>
                  <p>This Deſcription of Faith is thus illuſtrated unto us.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap. 5.</hi> Of the Deſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Faith.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. God makes a Promiſe of Eternal Life, and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereunto of the grace of Adoption, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of Sins, and the gift of the Holy Ghoſt. Thus God gives his Faith unto man, is Gracious to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, being moved thereunto only by his free love in Chriſt, without our ſupplication, or the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any Creature.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. God ſtands to his Promiſe thus made, and keeps his Faith; <hi>for he is faithful that hath promiſed, and keepeth Covenant for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Man accepts and entertains this Promiſe made by God, which is a taking of the Faith given, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting firmly to the giver for the full performance of it in due time.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Man makes a Promiſe to God, that is, he gives his Faith to God, to work that righteouſneſs which God hath required at his hands, by the help of his grace.</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:93356:9"/>
                  <p n="5">5. Man ſtands to his promiſe and Faith, which he hath given to God, by the performance of that duty of Love, which God hath required of him, with all his heart, ſoul, and ſtrength, by the ſame Grace.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. God accepts this Promiſe or Faith which man hath given to him, that is, God takes his Faith gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and truſteth to the Giver, expecting the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of it.</p>
                  <p>This is a mutual Contract betwixt God and Man, as that in Marriage, a mutual Aſſent and Conſent, giving and taking of each other.</p>
                  <p>This is the Covenant of Grace made between God and man,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap. 6.</hi> Of the Covenant of Grace.</note> whereby both parties are made ſure together: This is our Faith.</p>
                  <p>God reveals his Promiſe, Law, Will, Word, Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Covenant, Ordinance, Grace; God calls, moves, perſwades, draws, invites, allures, by all gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and proper means, fit for a rational ſpirit to receive.</p>
                  <p>When the heart hears, underſtands, is invited, moved, perſwaded and drawn, that is, accepts and embraces the offer of Grace, then man believes.</p>
                  <p>When the Heart ſtoppeth the Ear at the voice of this Charmer, though he charm never ſo often, never ſo wiſely; when he refuſeth, rejecteth, or embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth not, then man disbelieves, then he is condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of himſelf, becauſe he maketh God a Liar, who is Truth its ſelf, and cannot lye. As when a Rebel hath pardon offered by his Prince, and will not accept it upon the condition of future Loyalty, he
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93356:9"/>deſerves to dye, if he had ten thouſand lives.</p>
                  <p>So when the heart hath once accepted the free grace and love of God, and afterwards falls off, and embraces this preſent World, being weary of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and unwilling to exerciſe mortification and ſelf-denyal; then man is ſaid to deny the Faith, and to make Shipwrack of Faith, and of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
                  <p>So then the Acceptation of Gods good Word and Promiſe is True Faith, and by it the Believer obtains Righteouſneſs, even the Righteouſneſs of God which is by Faith.</p>
                  <p>And this is our Juſtification,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap. 7.</hi> Of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> that is not only to the forgiveneſſe of our ſins, but to a preſent Right of being the Child of God, and Heir of God, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heir with Jeſus Chriſt, and hath thereby the Spirit of God given unto him, which is the earneſt Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Aſſurance of his Salvation, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly hath Hope of the future Poſſeſſion of the Inheritance which is by Promiſe. And thus the juſt man lives by his Faith, and waits patiently upon God for the fulfilling of his word. And this his Faith ſtayes his Soul from fainting, and is unto him the Subſtance of things which are yet to come, and otherwiſe as to him do not ſubſiſt, and is unto him the Evidence of things not ſeen, and otherwiſe as to any mortal Eye, cannot be ſeen.</p>
                  <p>Thus <hi>Abraham</hi> believed in God, and it was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted unto him for Righteouſneſs, that is, <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> believed in God and thereby was juſtified; for St. <hi>Paul</hi> alledgeth theſe words to prove the Doctrine
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93356:10"/>of Juſtification by Faith: and to account any Right to any perſon, is to juſtify that Perſon, or to have Righteouſneſs imputed to him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. So had <hi>Abraham</hi> a true Right by his Faith to have a Son and a numerous Progeny, and to poſſeſs the Land of <hi>Canaan.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this is our Evidence alſo, That
<list>
                        <item>1. We have a Right to Heaven by Faith.</item>
                        <item>2. We hold it by Works.</item>
                        <item>3. We expect it by Hope.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>So Faith is a Paſſive Act of the Will, receiving, holding and embracing Gods offer; as the Fathers that were perſwaded of the Promiſes of God, and ſaw them a far off and embraced them; as they that heard the word,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13.</note> and received it with joy: And to as many as received Chriſt which was the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Seed,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luc.</hi> 8.13.</note> to them gave he Power, that they ſhould be called the Sons of God.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12.</note> So it is a Paſſive Act of the ſame Will, to refuſe or reject what is offered, as the Text ſpeaks — <hi>See that ye refuſe not him that ſpeaketh from heaven. — He that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecteth me, and receiveth not my words, hath one that judgeth him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.25. <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.48.</note> &amp;c. Thus the Lawyers rejected the Counſel of God againſt themſelves, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore accounted themſelves unworthy of Eternal Life.</p>
                  <p>Gods Promiſe imputes a Preſent Right to a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Bleſſing,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap. 8.</hi> Gods Promiſe.</note> which are two Acts of Gods will. Hence God requires an Acceptation of that preſent Right, and an Expectation of the future Bleſſing, which are two Acts of mans Will, correſpondent
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93356:10"/>to the two Acts of Gods Will, of imputing a Preſent Right, and a future Poſſeſſion of a Bieſſing.</p>
                  <p>This is Gods Promiſſory Will, which is not at all compulſatory, but invitatory, altogether leaving us freely to our own choice. And this Acceptance is Faith, and this expectance is Hope agreeable to the will of Gods Promiſe.</p>
                  <p>Thus Gods Precept, which is the condition of his Promiſe, impoſes a preſent Band to a future ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of ſome Duty, as the works of love,<note place="margin">Chap. 9. <hi>God's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>recept.</hi>
                     </note> which are two Acts of Gods Preceptory Will. Hence God requires ſubmiſſion to this preſent Band, and performance of the future Duty, which are two Acts of mans will, agreeable to the two Acts of Gods Will.</p>
                  <p>This is Gods Preceptory will, and this is compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatory, not Invitatory to leave us free to our own choice to obey, or to tranſgreſs, but legally binds us to obedience. And this obedience if freely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, not for fear of Puniſhment, is Love, which is the fulfilling of the Law in an Evangelical way.</p>
                  <p>Gods Precepts are his Revealed Will or Word, proceeding from his Holineſs; and Gods Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are his revealed Will or Word, proceeding from his Anger: But Gods Promiſes are his revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Will or Word, proceeding from his Love. This is Gods good Word, or his good Promiſe.</p>
                  <p>Therefore an Aſſent to Gods Precepts and to his Judgments, is Faith to convict a Sinner of his Tranſgreſſions, and the guilt of Puniſhment due to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93356:11"/>him for the ſame: But an Aſſent to Gods Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and an Acceptance of them, is faith to juſtify to a preſent Right to a future Bleſſing.</p>
                  <p>Thus <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Sarah,</hi> accepted the preſent Right, and expected the future bleſſing by faith and Hope.</p>
                  <p>And ſo the faithful accept the preſent Right, and expect the future Bleſſing by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and have it by Faith and Hope.</p>
                  <p>And though we dye before we poſſeſs it: yet we dye in faith, and lye down in hope to riſe again to the poſſeſſion of Eternal Glory. For ſo the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful are ſaid to be perſwaded of Gods promiſes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſeen them a far off, and imbraced them—<hi>All theſe dyed in faith,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 11.13.</note> 
                     <hi>having not yet received the full fruition of the Promiſes, and their fleſh reſted in hope to put on a glorious and bleſſed Immortality. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Deerly beloved Brethren, be ye ſtedfaſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable, allwayes abounding in the work of the Lord, foraſmuch as ye know, that your labour is not in vain in the Lord. For Faith is the ſubſtance of things hoped for, and the evidence of things not ſeen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Coroll. </seg>
                     </label> This faith is a Paſſive Act of mans Will, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and embracing that ſtate or condition into which Gods love puts us, to have a preſent Right to a future Reward.</p>
                  <p>Thus in making faith, the Action is on Gods part; and in taking faith, the Action is on Mans part. And this is noble and free in God to promiſe and perſwade, and in Man to be perſwaded and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive what God gives. What can be more eaſy
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93356:11"/>and reaſonable, then to ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to Gods Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, only this <hi>Fiat quod dicitur, Lord here I am to do whatſoever thou wilt have me to do.</hi> Thus the Bleſſed Virgin anſwered; <hi>Be it unto me even as thou haſt ſaid. Give Lord for thy ſervant is ready to receive,</hi> And that with a glad heart too, to obtain ſuch rich Grace from the God of all Grace.</p>
                  <p>This is Gods drawing of us with the Cords of a Man, which makes his Yoke eaſy, and his Burden light, and all that refuſe to be perſwaded are left without all excuſe. For how often hath God ſtood at their door and knockt, how often would he have gathered them together into his congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to be partakers of his Benefits with his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full People, but they would not; therefore theſe things are juſtly hid from their Eyes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap. 10.</hi> Of both Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants.</note>This is to be in Covenant with God, When Gods Sponſions are Double Acts of his Will, devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a preſent Right to a future Bleſſing, and Mans Reſponſions are Double Acts of mans Will, accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this preſent Right to a future Glory. And ſo our will becomes agreeable to Gods will, touching one thing to be had of God, which makes a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Covenant of Grace juſtly ſo called, becauſe God was moved to make that Covenant meerly by his Grace, and becauſe the Matter of it is very gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious. So Gods Commands are Double Acts of his Will for a preſent obligation to a future duty, and mans yeeldings are double Acts of his Will, to a preſent Band to a future duty. So our Will becomes agreeable to Gods Will, touching
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93356:12"/>one Thing to be done of man, which makes a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Covenant of Works juſtly ſo called, becauſe mans duty is a work, and the matter of it is Labour. For God Covenanted with <hi>Abraham,</hi> that he ſhould walk before God, and be upright, and that every male of his ſhould be Circumciſed. And God co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants with us, <hi>That we ſhould be poor in Spirit, mourn,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.</note> 
                     <hi>hunger and thirſt after Righteouſneſs, be pure in heart, merciful, meek,</hi> &amp;c. which is laborious.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>
                     </label> Therefore Gods Promiſe is a Covenant of Grace, and Gods Precept is a Covenant of works, and Gods Judgment is a Covenant of Curſes, which we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly enter into, but the two former willingly.</p>
                  <p>Therefore a full Right, Intereſt, Claim or Title of an Inheritance to come, together with an earneſt penny given and received, is the ſubſtance and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of that inheritance to the Heir thereof, and he is as ſure if he hold his Right given, as if he actually enjoyed it.</p>
                  <p>Therefore the Scripture ſaith,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.3.</note> 
                     <hi>We are already in heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus. And God hath raiſed us up together, and made us to ſet in heavenly places in Chriſt—He that Believeth hath everlaſting life,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.6.</note> 
                     <hi>and I will raiſe him up at the laſt day. —Chriſt is the firſt fruits of them that ſleep.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now if the firſt fruits be holy, then the whole Lump is holy. If Chriſt be the firſt fruits of the Reſurrection to Glory, then all that are Chriſts, even the whole Harveſt of the Faithful, ſhall riſe to the ſame Glory. And therefore Chriſt is called the Firſt Born from the Dead, our Elder Brother, the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93356:12"/>firſt Born among many Brethren; and if the firſt Born be riſen, then ſhall the ſecond and third Born, and all the Brethren that are born of the ſame God, riſe from the Dead, and be partakers of the ſame Inheritance of Glory with Chriſt their Elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in whom, and by whom they have right to be the ſons of God by the Grace of Adoption and Regeneration, as he had by Nature and Generation.</p>
                  <p>If Chriſt be the Head, then the Faithfull are the Body. And if the Head be riſen, the Body ſhall follow after. For our Fleſh is in Heaven already. And as ſure as Chriſt is in Heaven, ſo ſure ſhall we be alſo. For where he is, there we ſhall alſo be, and Chriſt is gone before to prepare a place for us, that where he is, there we might alſo be. And in his Fathers houſe there are many Manſions and Portions for all his Children. And where the Carcaſs is, thither will the Eagles be gathered together.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Application.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 12. <hi>Of Comfort.</hi>
                     </note>For Comfort and ſatisfaction to all. Godlineſs hath the Promiſe of this life, and of that which is to come.</p>
                  <p>Things to come are made Preſent, and things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen are made to be ſeen by Faith. God will have us to walk here by Faith, and hereafter by ſight.</p>
                  <p>Here we believe and ſee a farre off, hereafter we ſhall enjoy and ſee cleerly.</p>
                  <p>Here we know and ſee darkly as in a Glaſs, there we ſhall ſee Face to Face, and know even as we our ſelves are known.</p>
                  <p>We are ſure we are now the Sons of God, we
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93356:13"/>know not yet what we ſhall be, but this we know, that when Chriſt ſhall appear, we ſhall appear alſo with him in Glory.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap. 12.</hi> Of Priviledges by Faith.</note>For look what Right Chriſt hath by Nature to the Love of his Father, who hath made him Heir of all things, The ſame in kind, though not in degree, have we by Grace in and through Jeſus Chriſt, to be the Heirs of God, and Coheirs with Chriſt Jeſus; and conſequently, as younger brothers, to Taſt of the ſame Inheritance.</p>
                  <p>By Faith we ſee and feel theſe abſent and inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things of God, and know the heighth, and length, and depth, and breadth of the Love of God in Chriſt Jeſus, which otherwiſe paſſeth all knowledge; For neither Eye hath ſeen, nor Ear hath heard, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath it entred into the heart of man to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, what things God hath laid up for thoſe that fear Him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 13. <hi>Of Aſſurance.</hi>
                     </note>Evidence and Aſſurance. Faith, and the Spirit of God, are both theſe to our Spirits.</p>
                  <p>In the exerciſe of my Prieſtly office, I have oft heard the ſad complaints of poor devout Souls for want of Aſſurance; and that they had not intereſt in Chriſt, no faith, no comfort, they could not pray, nor do any good, and God had forſaken them. And alas, what ſhould they do?</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 14. <hi>Miſerable Comforters.</hi>
                     </note>To this, unskilful men, Phyſitians of no value, miſerable comforters, ſuch as preach Chriſt out of no good will, but envy eternal happineſs to others, and would engroſs it wholly to themſelves, make many ſad anſwers. Their Eye is evil, becauſe Gods
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93356:13"/>is good; niggardly Stewards to a Bountiful Maſter. Whereas they ought freely to give, as they have freely received, and diſpenſe the miſteries of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with a moſt bountiful hand. Hard Fathers, that had rather give a Stone, then an Egge, and a Scorpion rather then a Fiſh, of Soure, Sullen, Ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Saturnine Aſpect to ſome, driving them into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, calling them Reprobates, ſuch as have no ſhare in Gods Promiſes. Theſe men are farre from our Saviours Temper, who came to ſeek and to ſave that which was loſt, to call ſinners to Repentance, to Preach the Goſpel to the poor, Deliverance to the Captives, Recovery of ſight to the blind, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim the acceptable year of the Lord. The ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Flaxe he did not quench, and the bruiſed Reed he did not break; and of thoſe that came unto him he rejected none, but invited all that were heavy laden with the burden of their ſins, that they might find reſt to their Souls. They have forgotten the Precept of the Apoſtle, <hi>Let the ſame mind be in you, that was in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>On the contrary, they are fair, frolike, boon, buxome and debonair to themſelves, and to ſuch as are of their own Phariſaical Sect. They can ſow pillowes under every ſuch Elbow, and dawb with untempered morter, and Preach pleaſing things to ſuch as fill their Purſes.</p>
                  <p>Theſe can make a great gain of Godlineſs, can make it the faſhion to move ſcruples, and create doubts and fears in the tender conſciences of poor Creatures, teach them to whine and cry as a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93356:14"/>in her pangs, and call this the ſpiritual Throwes of the New-birth: but they muſt come to them to be their Midwives, and to reſolve all their doubts, and be delivered from all their fears; and thereout ſuck they no ſmall advantage.</p>
                  <p>They have ſet up an Aſſurance-office, and to them theſe Adventurers muſt come to ſecure them for their proſperous voyage to Heaven.</p>
                  <p>They can make a Fair and Market for Pardons, as well as the Papiſts by their Indulgences. 'Tis the ſame trick under a diverſe and more cleanly conveyance.</p>
                  <p>The ſame thing is done by their aſſurances, as is done by the Popiſh pardons.</p>
                  <p>They cauſe poor Souls to pin their ſalvation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their ſleeves, to hang their hopes upon their Teachers Girdles, and make the Diſciples live or dye by the Breath of their mouths, ſtand or fall, thrive or be undone by their ſmile or frown: In a word have abſolute dependance from them.</p>
                  <p>This is to Lord indeed over mens ſoules, and yet theſe men ſhall be admired, and humbly ſought unto by Rich Preſents, and glad they can get a glance or nod from the man of God. Thus they lead along multitudes, carrying them like Pitchers by the Eares, in as much ignorance and ſecurity, as the ſubtileſt Jeſuits or any other Orders can do.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe of their ſelect flock ſhall be the elect, and never fail. Slips and frailties may be in the Babes of Grace, but come to them, and all ſhall be made up again. God ſees no ſin in them, and they are in Heaven already.</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:93356:14"/>
                  <p>As for others they ſhall be Reprobates and Caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awayes, ſuch as have the Mark of the Beaſt, no ſignes of Grace nor Evidences for heaven at all.</p>
                  <p>Let the World take heed of theſe men, both amongſt us, and the Church of Rome.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap. 15.</hi> Of reſo ving of Doubts.</note>But they that are the True Interpreters of Gods Word, few among thouſands, that are able to ſpeak a word of comfort in due ſeaſon to weary ſoules; Theſe can ſhew unto man his Righteouſneſs by Faith, and ſave a ſoule alive, plucking them out of the Jaws of deſpair, and to find a Ranſome for them.</p>
                  <p>What heart ſo mercileſs, that will not, having power, draw a poor Captive out of the Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon?</p>
                  <p>To ſuch ſoules as theſe that are thus fearful I would ſay as Chriſt did, fear not, be of good cheer, thy Faith hath ſaved thee, <hi>Why do ye doubt, O ye of little faith?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To theſe I ſay, they have Faith, and have an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Chriſt; becauſe they deſire it, and do their utmoſt endeavour to pleaſe God.</p>
                  <p>And what if they feel no comfort, nor can find theſe marks men talk of, and can not pray eloquent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nor preach, is this for want of Grace? You know what the Scripture ſaith, — <hi>Lord, have we not taught in the ſtreets, and in thy name caſt out Devils, and done many mighty works;</hi> yet for all this, <hi>Depart from me, for I know you not, ye workers of Iniquity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nay, their ſpirits do pray, though their tongues want utterance, and the Spirit helpeth their infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93356:15"/>with ſighes and groans which they cannot utter.</p>
                  <p>And ſurely if they be asked, if they would part with the hopes that they have in Chriſt, they would not do it for ten thouſand Worlds.</p>
                  <p>This is their Caſe and Condition; They have lowly diſpoſitions of mind, the beſt of all; and they have melancholy tempers of Body, the worſt of all. This is the true cauſe of their ſpeaking after this manner from their ſenſe and reaſon, not from their Faith.</p>
                  <p>And as for Aſſurance, what Aſſurance would theſe men have? Would they look into Gods Book, and ſee their names written in the kingdome of Heaven; or is there any ſuch Book; or if there were, Do they look for a ſpecial Revelation? This is an unreaſonable requeſt, wherefore ſerves Faith? but to be <hi>the ſubſtance of things hoped for, and the evidence of things not ſeen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If they yet urge and ſay, they feel no comfort, I anſwer. Let them be content to want the ſenſe of Comfort, Faith is all in all to ſupply all our Wants, and there is joy and comfort enough in Believing; For I believe what I feel not, what I underſtand not. I live by Faith, and not by ſenſe. I believe againſt hope, and above hope, and contrary to hope. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not define what Faith is: but this I can tell, that I do believe, and I know in whom I truſt; and though I know not how the grace of God comes into my heart, nor when, yet I believe that I have it; and though the Lord kill me, yet will I truſt in him.</p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:93356:15"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap. 16.</hi> Faith about ſenſe.</note>Remember <hi>Abraham.</hi> The Promiſe was made to him, that he ſhould have a Son though he was old, and <hi>Sarah</hi> was paſt Child-bearing, inſomuch that ſhe laughed, and ſaid, <hi>Shall Sarah which is old bear, my Lord being old alſo?</hi> Yet <hi>Abraham</hi> believed, that God was faithful that had promiſed, and able to raiſe up Seed unto him, (though he knew not how) though it were out of the very ſtones. And <hi>Sarah</hi> believed alſo, elſe ſhe could not have conceived; but by her Faith ſhe did conceive, and the Child was the Child of Promiſe, by the mighty Power of God, above the ſtrength of Nature.</p>
                  <p>And again, when that Son was born and grown towards maturity, God commanded him to be ſlain, what hopes had <hi>Abraham</hi> then? Yet he ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered not, but believed ſtill, and God counted it unto him for Righteouſneſs.</p>
                  <p>Thus <hi>Job</hi> was tempted by his Wife to truſt no more in God: <hi>Doſt thou not ſee, how thy goods are conſumed with fire from heaven, Thy children all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by the fall of a houſe upon their heads, And thou thy ſelf art forſaken of thy friends, and ſmitten in thy Body, art a very Dunghil upon a Dunghil, And doſt thou retain thine integrity ſtill? Wilt thou ſerve ſuch a God, that rewards his ſervants no better? Curſe God to his face and ſo dye, for 'tis to no purpoſe to ſerve him any longer.</hi> But what ſaid <hi>Job, Thou ſpeakeſt like one of the fooliſh women. Doſt thou think that we ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive good at the hands of God, and not receive evil alſo? Though he kill me, yet will I truſt in him. In all this</hi> Job <hi>ſinned not, nor ſpake unadviſedly with his Lips, nor charged God fooliſhly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:93356:16"/>
                  <p>Thus <hi>David,</hi> according to ſenſe, was almoſt gone, his feet had well nigh ſlipt, when he conſidered his own ſufferings and the proſperity of the ungodly, Till he went unto the Sanctuary of God, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered better, and then he condemned himſelf for being ſo fooliſh and ignorant, and even as a Beaſt before God.</p>
                  <p>What think ye of Chriſt himſelf? Was he not a man of Sorrows, and acquainted with Griefs; and there was no beauty in him, and men hid their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from him, and he was deſpiſed and rejected of men, and endured the contradiction of Sinners, and there was no ſorrow like unto his ſorrow, Did he not cry out in his Agony upon the Croſs, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> Was he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore quite forſaken, becauſe he ſuffered ſuch things? Was he not the Son of God, and the Beloved of God ſtill, Though he felt no comfort for a time, while he grapled in the fearful Dark, and no Beam of comfort did ſhine upon him?</p>
                  <p>And if theſe things were done to the green-Tree, well may they be done to the dry.</p>
                  <p>If the Lord himſelf was thus ſerved, do we think to fare better then he? It is well for us, if we be as our Maſter.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Jonah</hi> was in the Whales Belly, and was gone down to the bottom of the Mountains, and the Earth with her barrs was about him as he thought in the judgement of his fleſh and bloud, for ever; and the weeds of Deſpair were wrapped about his head, that he had little hope in reaſon ever to ſee
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93356:16"/>the light of the Sun more; yet by his Faith did he raiſe up his mind to look up once more towards the holy Temple of God, and cry for Deliverance, and it was granted unto him.</p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> was in long and great diſtreſs, when he had a Thorne in the Fleſh, and the meſſenger of Satan was ſent to buffet him, who in his fierce wrath did lay ſore ſtripes upon him, which made him pray once and again, and yet he was not delivered; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs this Anſwer was given him from God, That <hi>his grace ſhould be ſufficient for him:</hi> and this ſtayed his ſpirit, and kept him from Deſpair.</p>
                  <p>And what though my condition be ſad, and ſo, that I have little or no joy in this World? And what if I ſhould go mourning from my Cradle to my Grave? If it be the will of God, I will bear it. I will ſay to my ſoul, <hi>Why art thou ſo vexed, and why is my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſo diſquieted within me,</hi> Put thy truſt ſtill in God, and he will cauſe every thing to work together in the end for his own glory and for the good of all ſuch as fear him. I reckon, that all the Afflictions of this life, are not worthy of the glory that ſhall be revealed.</p>
                  <p>I cannot tell the Reaſons of Gods workings, but this I am ſure, that though the wayes of God are often ſecret, yet they are alwayes juſt, and the Judge of the World muſt needs do right; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he can and will do me no wrong. Here there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am under his hand, as the Clay is under the hands of the Potter, <hi>Let him do with me what ſeemeth good in his own eyes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:93356:17"/>
                  <p>I am content, and count it an honor to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to Chriſt in his ſufferings; and this I gather by my Faith, That if I ſuffer with him, I ſhall alſo be glorifyed with him. And therefore in my Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence I poſſeſs my ſoul ſtill, and count it good to wait upon God; though I ſee and feel no comfort, yet I will ſtay till it comes, and it will come and will not tarry; and though it never come, yet will I ſerve my God, and I know in whom I have truſted: My heart is fixed upon the ſure mercies of <hi>David,</hi> and there I caſt Anchor: I build my Houſe upon this Rock of Chriſt; and though the Windes do bluſter, and the Waves rage and rore horribly, yet I am ſure I ſhall not ſink under them, nor ſplit upon the Rocks of Deſpair.</p>
                  <p>Though I do ſtick deep in the Mire and Clay, and the Waves go over my head; nay, though I be trod upon as the dirt in the ſtreets: yet I have a God ſtill that owns me, and knows my ſoul in all its Adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and <hi>will never leave me nor forſake me.</hi> Though my father and my mother forſake me, and all the comforts of this life take wings and fly away from me, yet I will go unto my God, and to the Throne of his Grace, for Grace ſufficient to help me in the time of all my need. Out of the Deep therefore will I cry unto God, and he will hear my voice, and in his due time and in his own way he will deliver me from all my fears.</p>
                  <p>When the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had the Red-Sea before them, and their Enemies behind them, that there ſeemed to be no hope, but that they muſt be ſwallowed up
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93356:17"/>one way or other; yet then they were bidden to ſtand ſtill, and ſee the ſalvation of God, who made bare his Arme, and ſtretched forth his right Arme to ſave them.</p>
                  <p>Be not therefore affrighted, O ye faithful ſoules,<note place="margin">Chap. 16. <hi>Counſel.</hi>
                     </note> at the multitude and ſtrength of Temptations and miſeries here in this World: know this, that there are more with you, then are, or poſſibly can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you. It is Chriſt that is your Captain, March under his Banner againſt the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil, and at laſt you ſhall be more then Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors, and ſhall tread Satan under every one of your feet.</p>
                  <p>Be not troubled for want of Aſſurance. This is your Aſſurance, That you believe in the Son of God. I demonſtrate comfort Thus,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. God is Faithful that hath Promiſed, he can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fail.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Chriſt is faithful, in whom, and to whom the Promiſes are made, and he can never fail; for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is ſure to all the Seed.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Holy Ghoſt is faithful that Seals the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God to our Souls, and he can never fail, The Spirit of promiſe to all the Seed.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Therefore the faithful that receive and rely upon theſe Promiſes, ſhall never fail; for they are in Chriſt the Promiſed Seed. As for fleſh and blood, though that be weak, and afflictions very grievous to it; yet let the ſpirit be but honeſt and willing, and then fear nothing. For to him that hath, though never ſo little, true faith ſhall be given; full mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93356:18"/>preſſed down and running over, ſhall God give into his boſome. To him that is never wanting to himſelf, God will never be wanting. Do but deſire, and God will help, do but ſeek, and thou ſhalt find, ask and have, knock and it ſhall be opened unto thee. <hi>If we that are evil, know how to give good things to our Children, how much more ſhall our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly father give good things to them that ask him.</hi> And hath he not promiſed, that whatſoever we ſhall ask of him in the Name of his Son, he will give it us; and having given us Chriſt, how ſhall he not with him alſo give us all things that he in his wiſdome and goodneſs knows to be neceſſary for us? And having our Portion, let us therewith be content.</p>
                  <p>Look therefore Sin, Miſery and Death in the face, and Truſt in God ſtill.</p>
                  <p>Look only upon Sin, and Miſery, and Death, and Hell with the Eye of Senſe, and dye for fear and deſpair: but look with the Eye of Faith beyond all theſe at the glory that ſhall be revealed, and live for evermore.</p>
                  <p>Conſult not with fleſh and blood; for if you do, you will droop and fall: but conſult with the Spirit by Faith in Gods Promiſes, and he ſhall ſtrengthen thine heart.</p>
                  <p>I have nothing to comfort and ſatisfy me and aſſure me in life or Death, but my honeſt and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful deſires. If I be a Hypocrite, I can have no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; but if I be true and upright to God, to the World, and to my own ſoul, and do all I can to pleaſe God, and to keep my Conſcience void of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93356:18"/>offence towards God and towards men, though I am clothed with innumerable frailties, and imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet I am ſure God will pardon all for Chriſt his ſake; only let me be valiant and of a good courage.</p>
                  <p>And though I ſee no comfort coming to me in this life, or very little, let me not be diſheartened for this, nor judge of Gods favour by what I ſee or feel, but by what I believe and hope for; for the things which are ſeen or felt are but Temporal: but the things which are not ſeen nor felt here, are Eternal. And what I ſee not and enjoy not now by ſenſe, I do ſee and enjoy by Faith, and ſhall ſee and enjoy by ſight. And till then I content my ſelf with the ſight and fruition which I have, which is to me an Evidence and full Aſſurance of what I ſhall have.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore, Deerly beloved Brethren, be ye ſtedfaſt and unmoveable, alwaies abounding in the work of the Lord, for as much as ye know that your labour ſhall never be in vain in the Lord; for faith is the ſubſtance of things ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for, and the evidence of things not ſeen.</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:93356:19"/>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:93356:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>GAL. 3.6. Abraham</hi> believed in God, and it was accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him for Righteouſneſs.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>EXPLICATION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Apoſtle ſaith —<hi>Righteouſneſs cometh not of the Law,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gal. 2.21. Gal. 3.18.</note> —<hi>And the Inheritance is not of the Law, but by Promiſe, and faith in that Promiſe.</hi> Both theſe ſayings carry the ſame ſenſe: that is, The right of an Inheritance (which is the beſt Right,) cometh not of the Law, but of Faith. And both theſe ſayings carry the ſame Reaſon, becauſe they argue the ſame Concluſion, <hi>viz.</hi> That a man is not Juſtified by the Law, but by Faith; For if a man be Juſtified by the Law, or if his Right of Inheritance be by the Law,<note place="margin">Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 4.14.</note> then Faith is made void, and the Promiſe void: But <hi>being juſtified by his Grace,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tit. 3.7.</note> 
                     <hi>we are made heirs to the hope of Eternal Life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that to be juſtified by Faith, and to be made an heir of God, are all one in effect, or the latter is but the property or conſequent of the former. In like manner to be counted Righteous, or as in the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93356:20"/>Text, for Faith to be counted for Righteouſneſs, is all one as to be juſtified; For St. <hi>Paul</hi> alledgeth theſe words to prove the Doctrine of Juſtification by Faith: and to have Right accounted to any perſon, is to juſtify that Perſon, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this great ſaying, <hi>That</hi> Abraham <hi>believed in God, and it was accounted to him for Righteouſneſs,</hi> is to this effect. That <hi>Abraham</hi> was juſtified by his Faith.</p>
                  <p>The Subject is Juſtification.</p>
                  <p>The Points, 1. God, 2. Account, 3. Thing, 4. End.</p>
                  <p>God the Cauſe of Juſtification:<note place="margin">Chap. 1. <hi>God juſtifi s. Rom.</hi> 8.33. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.6.</note> —It is God that juſtifieth, ſo the Hebrew Text; Abraham <hi>believed in God, and he imputed it to him for Righteouſneſs.</hi> God was the Agent that imputed Faith to <hi>Abraham</hi> for Righteouſneſs. St. <hi>Paul</hi> follows the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> but the ſenſe is all one. For if actually God imputed <hi>Abrahams</hi> Faith unto him for Righteouſneſs, then it muſt needs follow paſſively, that <hi>Abrahams</hi> Faith was imputed to him for Righteouſneſs.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Account.<note place="margin">Cap. 2. <hi>Accounting.</hi>
                     </note> The Word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is rendred, reaſoning, concluding, numbring, reckoning, impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
                  <p>The great Arts of counting are <hi>Logick</hi> and <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtick.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Logick</hi> is the counting of Sayings, according to their rations or reaſons, as they are compoſed into their Concluſions, and reſolved into their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Logiſtick</hi> is the counting of Numbers, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their rations or rates, as they are compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93356:20"/>into their Powers, and reſolved into their Roots.</p>
                  <p>And as in <hi>Logick</hi> the Concluſion is the effect of two Sayings rightly figured, when one of thoſe Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings is the cauſe of that effect, and the other Saying is the reaſon or mean between the Cauſe and the Effect: So in <hi>Logiſtick,</hi> The Power is the Product of two Numbers rightly multiplyed, when one of thoſe two Numbers is the Root of that Power, and the other is the Rate between the Root and the Power. Both theſe Countings or Reckonings, or Reaſonings, do manifeſt the ration or Rate of a Saying to a Saying, and of a Number to a Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
                  <p>So that to Account, is to conclude by Reaſoning or Numbring; by arguing to find the Concluſion; by addition to find the Total, by Multiplication the Product, by Diviſion the Quotient.</p>
                  <p>The Word is uſed thus in ſeveral places.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.11.</note> —<hi>Reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your ſelves to be dead unto ſin,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> 3 28. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18.</note>—<hi>Therefore we conclude that a man is juſtified by Faith,</hi> —<hi>I reckon that the ſufferings of this life, are not worthy of the glory that ſhall be revealed,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.19.</note> —<hi>Accounting that God was able to raiſe him up even from the dead.</hi> —<hi>We ſay, that Faith was reckoned to</hi> Abraham <hi>for Righteouſneſs.</hi> —<hi>The children of the Promiſe are counted for the ſeed.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.4.8.</note> —<hi>Now to him that worketh the reward is not counted of Grace but of Debt:</hi> —<hi>Bleſſed is the man to whom the Lord will not impute ſin.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.26.</note> —<hi>If the Circumciſion keep the Righteouſneſs</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Rights of the Law) <hi>ſhall not his uncircumciſion be counted for Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion?
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93356:21"/>—But to him that worketh not,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6.</note> 
                     <hi>but believeth on him, that juſtifyeth the ungodly, his faith is accounted for Righteouſneſs.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6.</note> 
                     <hi>— Bleſſed the man to whom the Lord imputeth Righteouſneſs without works.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. The thing accounted is Faith;<note place="margin">Chap. 3. <hi>Faith.</hi>
                     </note> that is, Faith was the Reaſon, whereby God concluded <hi>Abraham</hi> Righteous: Faith was the Medium that inferred that Concluſion. Gods Promiſe was the Cauſe, <hi>Abrahams</hi> Righteouſneſs was the Effect; <hi>Abrahams</hi> Faith was the means that produced this Effect from that Cauſe.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13.</note> —<hi>The Promiſe that he ſhould be the Heir of the World, was not to</hi> Abraham <hi>and his ſeed through the Law, but through the Righteouſneſs of Faith.</hi> So by Faith the Promiſe became effectual.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. This Faith was real in <hi>Abraham,</hi> and really im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to him for Righteouſneſs;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.20.</note> —<hi>he was ſtrong in Faith, giving glory to God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. This Faith was his own proper Faith; elſe how could he be accounted the Father of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, if the Faith accounted to him were not his own. So the Un-circumciſion which is counted for Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, is not another mans; but his own Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion to whom it is accounted. And that Sin, that is imputed, or not imputed, is not another mans ſin, but his own ſin. And that Righteouſneſs, which is accounted to any man, is not the Righteouſneſs of another; but his own Righteouſneſs to whom it is accounted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                     </label> Becauſe, When we account or impute to any perſon any thing that is not his own but another mans, our account is not right.</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:93356:21"/>
                  <p n="4">4. The End, for which Faith was accounted,<note place="margin">Chap. 4.</note> is Righteouſneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Righteouſneſs.</note> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is of various ſignification, as is the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and the Verb <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Legally it is taken for doing Right to all, or giving every one his due by Law.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ex.</hi> 23.7.</note> —<hi>The Innocent and Righteous ſlay thou not.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.3.</note> —<hi>He that ruleth over men muſt be Righteous:</hi> —Herod <hi>feared</hi> John Baptiſt,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.20.</note> 
                     <hi>knowing that he was a juſt man.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.6.</note> —Zachariah <hi>and</hi> Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth <hi>were both righteous before God, walking in all the Commandments and Ordinances of the Lord blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les;s.</hi> —Jacob <hi>s;aith,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 30.33.</note> 
                     <hi>So ſhall my Righteouſneſs anſwer for me. —Not for thy Righteouſneſs,</hi> &amp;c. Deut. 9.5. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 45.7. <hi>Thou loveſt Righteouſneſs,</hi> &amp;c. Prov. 16.8. <hi>Better is a little with Righteouſneſs, then great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues without Right: —He looked for Righteouſneſs,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſ.</hi> 5.7.</note> 
                     <hi>and behold a Cry: —He hath appointed a day,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 17.31.</note> 
                     <hi>in the which he will judge the World in Righteouſneſs. —He that doth Righteouſneſs is Righteous.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Morally for kindneſs and Courteſy, Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality and Bounty, giving more then is due by Law, through Love.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſ.</hi> 37.2.</note>—<hi>The Righteous ſheweth mercy and giveth. —The Righteous giveth and ſpareth.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.26.</note>—<hi>Stand ſtill that I may reaſon with you,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.7.</note> 
                     <hi>of all the Righteouſneſs of the Lord, which he did to you, and to your Fathers. He that hath clean hands, and a pure heart,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſ.</hi> 24.4.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhall receive the bleſſing from the Lord, and Righteouſneſs from the God of his Salvation. —He hath diſperſed abroad;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſ.</hi> 112.9.</note> 
                     <hi>he hath given to the poor; his Righteouſneſs remaineth for ever.—Seek ye firſt the kingdome of God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 6 3 3.</note> 
                     <hi>and his Righteouſneſs.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17.</note>—<hi>For therein the Righteouſneſs of God
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93356:22"/>is revealed from faith to faith;</hi> ſignifying the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God; becauſe oppoſed in the next verſe, to the wrath of God.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> 3.21.</note>—<hi>But now the Righteouſneſs of God, without the Law, is manifeſted.</hi> 1. The kindneſs, as it is taken <hi>verſ.</hi> 21, 25, 26. compare <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.7. where the Apoſtle, to expreſs the ſame thing, uſeth the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>—<hi>That he might ſhew the riches of his Grace, in his kindneſs towards us:</hi> So Tit. 3.4. <hi>After that the kindneſs and love of God appeared:</hi> kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs here, is the very ſame with Righteouſneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.10.</note>—<hi>Now he that miniſtreth ſeed to the Sower,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Increaſe the fruits of your Righteouſneſs,</hi> i. e. kindneſs in contributing to the poor Saints.—<hi>Take heed that you do not your Almes before men:</hi> The Right Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal there, is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> properly in the New-Teſtament is to do a kindneſs. And this ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was familiar to the Eaſtern Greeks in <hi>Aſia,</hi> after whoſe Idiom the New Teſtament was written:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſ.</hi> 60.21.</note> But to the Weſtern Greeks in <hi>Europe</hi> it was more ſtrange.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Jurally for Propriety,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſ.</hi> 69.28.</note> or Right.—<hi>Thy People ſhall be all Righteous, they ſhall inherit the Land for ever. — Let them be blotted out of the book of the Living,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſ.</hi> 118 20.</note> 
                     <hi>and not be written among the Righteous,</hi> i.e. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> the Righteous heirs of the Land, upon Record.—<hi>This Gate of the Lord into which the Righteous ſhall enter,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 30.33.</note> i. e. <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> for ſtrangers might not enter into the Temple: but remained in the outward Court.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſ.</hi> 35.27.</note>—<hi>So ſhall my Righteouſneſs anſwer for me in time to come,</hi> i. e. <hi>all the young ſpotted cattle, I have right to for my wages.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.8.</note> —<hi>Let them be glad that favour my Righteouſneſs,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſ.</hi> 5.23.</note> i. e. my Righteous Cauſe.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93356:22"/>—<hi>Better is a little with Righteouſneſs, then great reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues without Right. —Which juſtify the wicked for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.7.</note> 
                     <hi>and take away the Righteouſneſs of the Righteous from him.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5.</note> —Noah <hi>became Heir of the Righteouſneſs which is by Faith.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.</note> 
                     <hi>—His faith is counted for Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> — Abraham <hi>received the ſigne of Circumciſion, a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of the faith which he had, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uncircumciſed,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13.</note> 
                     <hi>that he might be the father of all them that believe;</hi> which was no Moral Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but a Jural Right of Dignity. —<hi>For the Promiſe that he ſhould be the Heir of the world, was not to</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, <hi>or to his ſeed through the Law, but through the righteouſneſs of Faith.</hi> Now promiſe, and Heir, are matter of Right: So the word Righteouſneſs ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies in divers places of this Epiſtle.</p>
                  <p>Compare <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.18. —<hi>For if the Inheritance be of the Law, it is no more of promiſe.</hi> What is meant in one place by <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a general word for Right, the ſame is expreſſed in the other, by the ſpecial word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the beſt kind of Rights. Alſo to have Right by the Law,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.14.</note> or to have the Inheritance by the Law, is the ſame in ſenſe. And then the Promiſe is fruſtrate—<hi>For if they which be of the Law, be heirs, Faith is made voyd, and the Promiſe made of no Effect.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Chap. 5. <hi>Right.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The word Righteouſneſs is taken in this laſt ſenſe jurally for <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Jus</hi> or Right; ſuppoſed in all Acts of Juſtice, Equity, and Righteouſneſs; oppoſed to Injuſtice, Iniquity, and Unrighteouſneſs.</p>
                  <p>For whenſoever any of theſe Acts are done to any perſon, that perſon is ſuppoſed to have ſome <hi>Jus</hi> or Right; otherwiſe we can do him no Injuſtice, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:93356:23"/>or Wrong. For as where there is no Law, there is no Sin; ſo to him that hath no Right, there can be done no wrong, as to Slaves.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Becauſe Right, ſignifies the effect of Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. God promiſed a Right of Alliance, Iſſue, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance; and therefore <hi>Abraham</hi> had a Right, Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and Intereſt to all theſe; elſe the promiſe had been unjuſt, and of no effect.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Becauſe the New Teſtament ſo expreſſeth it: <hi>But to him that worketh not,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 45.6.</note> 
                     <hi>but believ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th in him that juſtifieth the ungodly, his faith is counted for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs: Even as</hi> David <hi>alſo deſcribeth the Bleſſedneſs of the man, unto whom God imputeth Righteouſneſs without Works;</hi> So alſo in the 10, 11, 12, 13, 22, 23, 24 verſes of this Chapter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> Becauſe the Old Teſtament ſo expreſſeth it.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſ.</hi> 106.30, 31.</note> 
                     <hi>Then ſtood up</hi> Phinehas, <hi>and executed Judgment, and ſo the Plague ceaſed. And this was counted to him for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs to all generations for evermore.</hi> This gave him a Right to the Fee-ſimple of the Prieſthood, to him and to his Heirs for ever; for ſo the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter runs:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Num.</hi> 25.10, 11, 12.</note> —<hi>And the Lord ſpake unto</hi> Moſes <hi>ſaying,</hi> Phinehas <hi>the ſon of</hi> Eleazar <hi>the ſon of</hi> Aaron <hi>the Prieſt, hath turned my wrath away from the children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>(while he was zealous among them) that I conſumed not the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>in my jealouſy. Wherefore, behold I give unto him my Covenant of Peace, and he ſhall have it, and his ſeed after him, even the Covenant of an everlaſting Prieſthood; becauſe he was zealous for his God, and made an atonement for the Children of</hi> Iſrael. He had a Right to the Prieſthood before by
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:93356:23"/>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> his Birth; but this was a Corroboration for ever.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe all Rights conſiſt in accounting, which is their Eſſence; As that the uſe, fruit, or propriety of ſuch a thing, is accounted or reckoned to ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as belonging to him, and not to another.</p>
                  <p>Thus God by his promiſe accounted to <hi>Abraham</hi> a Seed to be multiplied into the higher Powers of Numbers, As into Squares, Cubes, Squares of Squares, Squares of Cubes, and Cubes of Squares, <hi>i.e.</hi> into Tens, Hundreds, Thouſands, and hundred Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and thouſand Thouſands; till they were num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berleſs as the Starres of Heaven. And the Root unto all theſe Powers, was but the Binary of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and <hi>Sarah;</hi> old, dry, and dead in Body: but young and lively in Faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Illuſtration. </seg>
                     </label> Thus the working ſervant hath Right to his wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, by the meanes of his work.</p>
                  <p>The Son that worketh not, hath right to his main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance by his Birth. The firſt born Son hath right to his Inheritance by his Majority or Primogeniture.</p>
                  <p>The Believer hath no Right by Birth, nor by Works, but by Faith only; of Grace, not of Debt. This Faith is but a perſonal Act,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 4 4.</note> but the right there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is a real, permanent, and hereditary Benefit.</p>
                  <p>Thus Right to Bleſſedneſs, was the effect; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Gods Promiſe was the Cauſe, and <hi>Abrahams</hi> Faith the means, whereby that Cauſe wrought this effect.</p>
                  <p>The ſumme is; God by his Promiſe counted to <hi>Abraham</hi> a Right, and accounted his Faith for a means to obtain that Right: So his Faith was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:93356:24"/>for his Right, and his Right was accounted to him for his Faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abrahams</hi> Rights were, Iſſue, Inheritance, and chiefly Alliance with God;<note place="margin">Chap. 6. <hi>Bleſſedneſs.</hi>
                     </note> therefore God is called the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> which is bleſſedneſs in the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract, <hi>i. e.</hi> Heavenly bleſſedneſs, not expreſly ſo mentioned, but contained in the Promiſe, which wiſe <hi>Abraham</hi> in his reaſoning well underſtood, though a farre off;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.19.</note> and made a right reckoning of it, <hi>accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that God was able to raiſe from the Dead.</hi> And that God was bountiful ſo to do, to be his exceeding great reward; every way for Iſſue, for Inheritance: but eſpecially for Eternal Life.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10.</note>—<hi>For he looked for a City, which hath foundations, whoſe builder and maker is God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.16.</note> —<hi>And he deſired a better Country, then the Land of</hi> Canaan <hi>was; even a heavenly, and a better life then this:</hi> For God is not a Benefactor to the Dead, while they are dead. He is not the God of the Dead, but of the Living. And therefore that he may again become to them a God, he raiſes them from the Dead unto Eternal Life; Becauſe that is the great Bleſſing which they want, and he only can gives, and it is fitting only for his children to receive; and therefore he hath prepared for them a City, even <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which is above, which is the Mother of us all:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luc.</hi> 20.35, 36.</note> 
                     <hi>Chriſt</hi> reaſoneth juſt ſo. —<hi>They which ſhall be counted worthy to obtain that World, and the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from the Dead, neither marry, nor are given in marriage; Neither can they die any more: but are equal unto the Angels, and are the children of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the children of the Reſurrection.</hi> Now that the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:93356:24"/>Dead are raiſed, even <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhewed in the Buſh, when he calleth the Lord, <hi>The God of</hi> Abraham, <hi>the God of</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and the God of</hi> Jacob; For he is not a God of the Dead, but of the Living; for all live unto him.</p>
                  <p>Now the Title that <hi>Abraham</hi> had to all theſe Rights, was not his generous Birth, nor his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous works; but his acceptation of Faith, <hi>Jus Fidei,</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.14. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11, 13. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.30. Faith-right oppoſed to Birth-right and Work-right.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ </seg>5</label> Becauſe accounting is the common <hi>Genus</hi> to both Juſtifying and Condemning, for Accounting is a Word larger then Juſtifying or Condemning; and therefore is the common <hi>Genus</hi> to them both, being acts of accounting.</p>
                  <p>To Juſtify is to acquit as juſt to ſome reward. To condemn is to adjudg as ſinful to ſome Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. —<hi>For I will not juſtify the Wicked.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> 23.7.</note> —<hi>The Lord will not leave him in his hand,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſ.</hi> 37.33.</note> 
                     <hi>nor condemn him when he is judged.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.8.</note> —<hi>Bleſſed is the man to whom the Lord will not impute ſin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>6</label> Becauſe <hi>Abrahams</hi> Tenure to hold this Right, was the obedience of the Faith by which he had that Right.</p>
                  <p>Therefore he was accounted Righteous, only by his Faith; but he kept his Righteouſneſs by his Love and Duty that proceeded from his Faith, as of the offering up of his Son.</p>
                  <p>And ſo he had a full aſſurance to himſelf of his own Faith, by which he obtained ſo much Right,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:93356:25"/>and by his works his Faith was made perfect.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jac.</hi> 2.21.</note> So the word <hi>Juſtify,</hi> ſignifies to hold as well as to have a Right.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>7</label> Becauſe, after Gods accounting <hi>Abraham</hi> righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, God confirms his Right by an Oath. —<hi>By my ſelf have I ſworn,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 22, 16.</note> 
                     <hi>ſaith the Lord, for becauſe thou haſt done this thing, and haſt not withheld thy Son, thine only Son; That in Bleſſing I will bleſs thee, and in mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying I will multiply thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The effect of this was;<note place="margin">Chap. 7. <hi>Oathes.</hi>
                     </note> That <hi>Abraham</hi> might claim that Right which he had to the Promiſes which God had made, and now obliged himſelf to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance. For <hi>Juramentum</hi> comes from <hi>Juro,</hi> and <hi>Juro</hi> from <hi>Jus Juris,</hi> becauſe the right and beſt uſe of an Oath is to confirme and decide rights; for when a Right is voideable, an oath makes it immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and when a Right is Litigious, an Oath decides, and puts it out of queſtion, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.16.</p>
                  <p>This was <hi>Juramentum Fidelitatis,</hi> to perform the Faith God had given by Promiſe: God ſwears Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty to his Homager, to Duſt and Aſhes, to be a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector and Benefactor unto him. Yea, when <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was dead,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.16.</note> he was not aſhamed to be called his God, and the God of <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> when dead, becauſe he had prepared for them a City. Now the Oath of fealty is uſually taken by the vaſſal to his Lord. A wiſe man may find cauſe to doubt, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be only reaſonable, or no.</p>
                  <p>Note by the way; That Gods Oath was volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, as all Oaths ſhould be; elſe all ſoul-Liberty is deſtroyed.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.2.</note> —<hi>Put I pray thee thy hand under my thigh,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:93356:25"/>and I will make thee ſwear,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Abraham</hi> prayed his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to ſwear; He was his ſlave born in his houſe, yet he forced him not in this. So <hi>Jacob</hi> to his Son <hi>Joſeph. If I have found grace in ſight,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.29.</note> 
                     <hi>put I pray thee thy hand under my Thigh, and deal kindly and truly with me; bury me not I pray thee in Aegypt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>7</label> Becauſe <hi>Abraham</hi> was legally and morally Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous before he believed the Promiſe,<note place="margin">Chap. 8. <hi>True Right. Gen.</hi> 13.14.</note> and yet h was not juſtifyed by that Righteouſneſs, nor by the Eſtimatory Faith which he had in God, as a great Benefactor, who was feared and worſhipped by him:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 13.4.</note> but when he received the Promiſes. That Promiſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry faith juſtified him,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.15.16.</note> 
                     <hi>i. e.</hi> gave him a Title to thoſe Promiſes, of Iſſue, Inheritance, and Alliance, even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Ceremonial work of Circumciſion fourteen yeers.</p>
                  <p>So that he was meerly juſtified by his Faith in the Promiſes <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.9. 'Till when, <hi>Abraham</hi> never made the leaſt mention of an Iſſue or Inheritance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>8</label> Becauſe it is the Scope of the Apoſtle, to prove Juſtification by Faith.—<hi>So then,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.7, 8.</note> 
                     <hi>they that are of Faith, are the children of faithful</hi> Abraham. And the Scripture foreſeeing that God would juſtify the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then through Faith, Preached before the Goſpel unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſaying, <hi>In thee ſhall all the Nations of the Earth be bleſſed.</hi> So then, They that are of Faith, are bleſſed with faithful <hi>Abraham.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Concl. </seg>
                     </label> Therefore, What Right had <hi>Abraham</hi> to ſuch an Iſſue, and ſuch an Inheritance, and Alliance, more then other men, whoſe Bodies were younger and ſtronger, but only this; That ſuch an Iſſue, Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:93356:26"/>and Alliance was counted, and unto him for His; and his Faith was counted unto him for the Reaſon of it, <hi>i. e.</hi> for his Title to it.</p>
                  <p>So what right hath the Servant, who worketh to his wages, but only that his wages are accounted to him for His, and his work is accounted to him for the reaſon of it.</p>
                  <p>And what Right hath the Son that worketh not to maintenance, more then the Servant, who wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, but only this; That maintenance is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him for His; and his Birth is accounted to him for the reaſon of it.</p>
                  <p>And what Right hath the firſt born Son to his Fathers Inheritance, more then his yonger Sons, who are born to his Father as well as he, but only this; That the Inheritance is counted to him for His; and his Primogeniture or Majority is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him for the reaſon of it, <hi>i.e.</hi> for his Title to it, which therefore is called his Birth-right: though that word be too wide; for it is his Primogeniture, or firſt Birth-right in order before the reſt, which giveth unto him his Right.</p>
                  <p>And ſo the Believer in God, who as to God, hath neither Works nor Birth, What right hath he to Bleſſedneſs more then an unbeliever, but only this; That Bleſſedneſs is accounted His; and his Belief is accounted to him for the Reaſon of it, <hi>i.e.</hi> for his Title to Bleſſedneſs.</p>
                  <p>Hence the Apoſtle mentioning matter of right in <hi>Abrahams</hi> caſe, conſtantly uſeth the Verb <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> which ſignifies to count, And reckoning, Ratioci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:93356:26"/>and Counting, are all one in effect in Logick and Logiſtick.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>APPLICATION.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. For Aſſurance, Evidence, and Satisfaction to all Believers, of their Right.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. To Adoption by Grace.</item>
                     <item>2. To Remiſſion of ſins.</item>
                     <item>3. To Sanctification by the Spirit.</item>
                     <item>4. To Audience at the Throne of Grace.</item>
                     <item>5. To every ordinance of God, Baptiſme, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6. To Reſurrection.</item>
                     <item>7. To Eternal Life.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. Aſſurance is Gods giving his Faith to us,<note place="margin">Chap. 9. <hi>Aſſurance.</hi>
                     </note> and we giving our Faith to him, which is our being in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God. And a mutual giving and taking of the Faith of each other, is to be made ſure to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Aſſurance is an Acceptation of the Act of Gods grace and pardon upon the condition of our obedience.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Aſſurance is the Acceptation of the Legacy and Gift of Eternal Life, deviſed to all the Faithful in Gods laſt Will and Teſtament, whereof <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is the Mediator.</p>
                  <p>This Promiſe, Deviſe or Gift of Gods Teſtament concerning the Inheritance of Eternal Life, is made primarily to Chriſt, who is the promiſed Seed, in whom all the Promiſes of God are <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Amen,</hi> who is the Principal Heir of all things, and the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:93356:27"/>do taſt of the ſame Inheritance by Faith, that the Promiſe might be ſure to all the Seed, who for Chriſt his ſake are made Heirs of God and Co-heirs with Chriſt, partakers of the ſame moſt precious promiſes by Grace and Adoption.</p>
                  <p>Which Promiſes are as ſure to the Adopted Sons of God by Grace, as they are to Chriſt the Eſſential Son of God by Nature.</p>
                  <p>This Act of Grace is freely made of God in and for Chriſt, in whom God is well pleaſed; in whom God hath reconciled all things to himſelf.</p>
                  <p>And this is the full and laſt unchangeable Will of God, confirmed by the Bloud of Chriſt; ſo that heaven and earth may faile: but not the leaſt Title of Gods Will and Teſtament ſhall ever fail. For the Foundation of God ſtandeth ſure, and God knoweth who are his; and all the faithful are Inſtituted written Heirs of God <hi>ex Aſſe,</hi> and there is no Diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heredation or Preterition of any faithful Soul.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Aſſurance is Gods accounting us for righteous for our Faith, or by the means of our Faith. And if God ſo accounts us to have Right to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven, what greater Aſſurance can there be?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                     </label> The Conſcience accuſeth, therefore no Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                     </label> The Conſcience of a Believer, doth not accuſe, nor can accuſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe God accuſeth not; and if God accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not, who can? If God juſtifies, who dare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne?</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:93356:27"/>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe the ſoul that believes, knows that ſhe believes, therefore knows that ſhe is thereby juſtified, and therefore cannot accuſe.</p>
                  <p>The Soul that lives in treſpaſſes and ſins, that Soul doth not believe; well therefore may that ſoul ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, and God accuſeth much more.</p>
                  <p>But the ſoul that lives not in treſpaſſes and ſins; that Soul believeth; and therefore that ſoul can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not accuſe, but excuſe, becauſe God excuſeth much more.</p>
                  <p>Say not therefore, O faithful ſoul? that thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience accuſeth thee, and that thou art in the ſtate of Damnation. Nay, It is not thy Soul that can ſay thus, but it is thy Fancy, thy Paſſion, thy Humor, thy Diſtemper, thy Diſeaſe, thy Temptation. Why then ſhouldeſt thou doubt, or ſpeak unadviſedly with thy lips, or charge God ſo fooliſhly, O thou of little Faith!</p>
                  <p>To reckon Right with God.<note place="margin">Chap. 10. <hi>Reckoning.</hi>
                     </note> God accounts thee to be Righteous for thy Faith, or by the means of thy Faith, and they that God account Righteous, are Righteous indeed, for God judgeth righteous Judgment, and makes a true accompt; therefore we may moſt ſafely reckon with God, as God reckons by the means of our Faith: Yea, we wrong God and our ſelves, if we do not.</p>
                  <p>Our reckoning then is upon Gods Promiſes, thoſe ſure mercies to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed; Therefore Chriſt came to performe the mercy promiſed to our Fore-fathers, and to remember his holy Covenant. For the hope of which promiſes, the twelve Tribes
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:93356:28"/>of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> even the children of the Promiſe, do inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerve God day and night: and to this Promiſe they hope aſſuredly to come, upon the ſtrongeſt grounds of Reaſoning and accounting, that can poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be made, even to a demonſtration that cannot be denyed.</p>
                  <p>For all Rights that do ariſe from any Promiſe,<note place="margin">Chap. 11. <hi>Promiſes.</hi>
                     </note> are conveyed to the party, to whom the Promiſe is made by no other means, but by Faith, <hi>i. e.</hi> by Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of the promiſe, and the right ſpecified therein.</p>
                  <p>For all Promiſes are made effectual by Faith, by his Faith to whom the promiſe is made; For if he be unbelieving and refuſe it, then the Promiſe is dead, and of one effect: but if he give Faith to it and accept it, then it binds him that made it, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it, and creates a Right to him that accepts it, to enjoy the benefit of it.</p>
                  <p>And the Reaſon is, becauſe Acceptance formes a Promiſe into a Covenant, whereby there is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening or meeting of minde unto minde, and will unto will, <hi>viz:</hi> the mind and will of the Receiver, to the mind and will of the Promiſer. Thus the Promiſe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13.</note> that <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhould be the Heir of the World, came not to him through the Righteouſneſs of the Law, but through the Righteouſneſs of Faith, <hi>i.e.</hi> not by any Act of the Law, but by the Act of his Acceptance. For as the Promiſe was an Act of meer Grace on Gods part that made it: So the Acceptance was a meer Act of Faith on <hi>Abrahams</hi> part that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:93356:28"/>
                  <p>And as between God and <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſo is the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of all Promiſes, and the Aſſurances of the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits by them.</p>
                  <p>To prove our Reckoning right.</p>
                  <p>In Ratiocination and Reckoning,<note place="margin">3. Chap. 12. <hi>Proof.</hi>
                     </note> there is a way to prove the Argumentation or Accompt to be free from fallacy or error, as wiſe Logicians and Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meticians uſe to do.</p>
                  <p>So every wiſe Chriſtian will prove his own Faith, by which he reckoneth upon his own Salvation, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be true or no.</p>
                  <p>And that muſt be by his Works.<note place="margin">Cap. 13. <hi>Works.</hi>
                     </note> For Works do declare this Right to Salvation to be truly conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and reckoned, and do juſtify that faith, by which we reckon our ſelves to be juſtified.</p>
                  <p>Note here, that Works do not make and create a Right, where there was none before: but do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt the right which was before made, but concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: My Faith doth create and make me to have a Right in Chriſt; but my Faith is a thing inviſible, ſpiritual, and concealed within my heart, I cannot ſee it, nor the World cannot ſee it, unleſs I ſhew it by the fruits thereof outwardly to God and Man.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jac.</hi> 2.18, &amp;c.</note> —<hi>A man may ſay</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>James</hi>) <hi>Thou haſt Faith, and I have Works, Shew me thy faith without thy Works, and I will ſhew thee my Faith by my Works.</hi> —<hi>Know O vain man, that faith without works is dead.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abraham</hi> was juſtified by Faith, when he embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Promiſes; but <hi>Abraham</hi> was juſtified by Works, when he offered up <hi>Iſaac</hi> his Son upon the Altar. <hi>Seeſt thou how Faith wrought with his works,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:93356:29"/>and by works was faith made perfect:</hi> And ſo the Scripture was fulfilled, which ſaith, Abraham <hi>belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved God, and it was imputed unto him for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Works therefore do perfect thy Faith, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare thy Faith to be perfect. Faith juſtifies before God, without the concurrence of works as to the meer act of Faith; but works juſtify Faith before men by their concomitancy with Faith. And though Faith gave thee a Right; yet works do demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to thy ſelf and to the World, that Faith hath been lively and operative, to give thee this Right and Intereſt in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Works therefore do perfect that Faith by which thou art juſtified, and Works do declare thee to be juſtified, becauſe they declare that Faith by the which thou art juſtified. Thy Faith alone doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure that Right to be juſtified, but thy Faith alone doth not declare that Right to me, which it creates and makes to thee: But thy Faith needs works to declare and prove both to thee and me that Right, which it hath created and made to thee, for thy great comfort and ſatisfaction, and the Glory of God and praiſe of good men.</p>
                  <p>I conclude therefore that Faith, makes a Right Reckoning with God; but Works prove this Right Reckoning to be right made.</p>
                  <p>But this is not all. For as Faith is the means whereby we have a Right and Title preſent to the future Poſſeſſion of the heavenly Promiſes: So works are the means whereby we hold the Right
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:93356:29"/>and Title preſent to the future Poſſeſſion of the heavenly promiſes, that we may maintain and keep our Right, and make a Right reckoning thereof unto the end; that our Faith fail us not, and that we may not come ſhort of the heavenly Glory.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.1.</note> —<hi>Let us therefore ſear leaſt a promiſe being l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ft us of entring into his reſt, any of you ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d ſeem to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ome ſhort of it.</hi> For ſome did not keep the Faith, but made ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack of it by their evil deeds; and therefore could not enter into the Temporal Reſt provided for them, becauſe of their unbelief.<note place="margin">Heb. <hi>3.</hi> ult.</note> —<hi>Let us therefore draw neer with a true heart in full aſſurance of Faith; having our hearts ſprinkled from an evil Conſcience, and our bodies waſhed with pure water.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22, 23, 24.</note> 
                     <hi>Let us hold faſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our Faith without wavering (for he is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that hath promiſed.) And let us conſider one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and provoke one another unto Love and good works,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. For comfort. Why ſhould Believers quarrel?<note place="margin">Chap. 14. <hi>Peace.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. We have all the ſame Cauſe of Right, which is Gods Promiſe.</item>
                     <item>2. We have all the ſame Right, the effect of Gods Promiſe, Juſtification.</item>
                     <item>3. We have all the ſame means, reaſon, or Title, whereby the ſame cauſe becomes effectual for the obtaining of that Right, which is Faith. Therefore we all agree in the main, and may and ought to be comforted thereby.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>How vain then and ſinful are thoſe queſtions and doubts, about the manner of Gods Promiſe, and our Right thereby, and the means of Faith, for the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:93356:30"/>conveyance of that Right unto us.</p>
                  <p>Brethren and fellow-heirs of the ſame Promiſe, have no Reaſon to fall out about the way and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how they come by them; it is ſufficient that they are ſure of them: and God be thanked for that. Let them love one another. Unjuſtly therefore do we hate and ſeparate one from another, ſeeing we all truſt in one God for the ſame common Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>And why ſhould we be diſheartned,<note place="margin">Chap. 15. <hi>Courage.</hi>
                     </note> or doubt any more of the Truth which is ſo evident: God is Faithful which hath promiſed; our Right is ſure which is promiſed; the Means to joyn both theſe together, and give us this right is ſure, even our Faith. Therefore do but believe, do not diſpute; All things are poſſible to him that believeth. Do but accept, and ye ſhall have; Take what is offered unto you. An eaſy Yoke, A light Burden, A noble way: A rational way to be drawn by the cords of a Man; by Love, for Love. To ſuffer our ſelves to be wrought upon, and perſwaded by Love. To be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that God is; That he is a Rewarder of all ſuch as fear him; That all that will accept of this Reward, ſhall have it upon this reaſonable and eaſy condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Faith and Repentance. That a new Life and Holineſs is a moſt pleaſant thing of its ſelf, if there were no other Reward. That if there be another Reward, it ought in reaſon, being ſo great as Eternal Life, to be enjoyed by them only that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, and that labour for it. That if there be no Reward; yet it is more juſt and comfortable to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:93356:30"/>hope well, and live well, then to deſpair and do all wickedneſs, to the preſent hurt of our own Peace, and the Diſturbance and Ruine of others, for which they will Curſe us even in this World. And if there be a Reward, as moſt certainly there is, then theſe men ſhall be ſure to miſs it, but the Faithful cannot fail to have it; Becauſe that reward is promiſed upon the Condition of Faith, and none other. As ſure as there is a God in Heaven: ſo ſure ſhall there be a Reward in Heaven. And as ſure as there is a Chriſt: ſo ſure ſhall all they be rewarded that are in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>As ſure as Chriſt is born the Son of God by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and the ſpirit: ſo ſure are the faithful born the Sons of God by Grace and the Spirit. As ſure as Chriſt was the promiſed Seed: ſo ſure are the Faithful the Promiſed Seed in him, and by him. As ſure as Chriſt is the Heir of all things in himſelf, by the means of his Birth-right: ſo ſure are the Faithful, the heirs of God by the means of their Birth-right. As ſure as God hath promiſed and ſworn to Chriſt: ſo ſure hath God promiſed and ſworn to the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
                  <p>This is Goſpel. God is a Spiritual Father; The Faithful are a Spiritual Seed, Spiritual Heirs of a Spiritual Inheritance.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. For Diſtinction of Reckoners true and falſe, and of ſuch as do not Reckon at all.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Some make no accompt,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap. 15.</hi> Kinds of recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note> being without God in the World, and having no Hope, ſtrangers to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Promiſe, dead while they live.</p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:93356:31"/>
                  <p n="2">2. Some make a falſe accompt, reckoning without Faith, Boaſting of a Right to an eſtate when they have no grounds for it: Living highly, and making a great ſhow to the World, of a portion in Heaven; when as they have nothing to truſt unto; being Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, whoſe hope ſhall periſh, and be cut off be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luc.</hi> 13.25, &amp;c.</note> Angels, and men. —<hi>They ſhall knock at the door, ſaying, Lord Lord open unto us; then ſhall the Maſter of the houſe anſwer and ſay unto them, I know you not whence you are.</hi> Then ſhall they begin to ſay <hi>We have eaten and drank in thy preſence, and thou haſt alſo taught in our ſtreets;</hi> but he ſhall ſay, <hi>I tell you, I know you not whence you are, Depart from me ye wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Iniquity.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.21, &amp;c.</note> —<hi>Not every one that ſaith unto me Lord Lord, ſhall enter into the kingdome of Heaven; but he that doth the will of my Father which is in heaven. Many ſhall ſay unto me in that day; Lord, Lord, have we not Prophecied in thy Name? and in thy Name caſt out Divels? and in thy name done many wonderful works? And then will I profeſs unto them, I never knew you, Depart from me ye workers of Iniquity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Some have a true accompt made by God for them, but cannot make a true accompt for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but are hindred and puzled, being weak, and put out of their reckoning.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. By ſchool diſtinctions without difference, and coy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned niceties, oppoſitions of Sciences falſly ſo called.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By Pulpit marks &amp; ſigns; the fancies of idle Brains, and multiplication of Words without knowledge.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. By private ſcornes and Reproaches of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation and Damnation, without Wit or Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:93356:31"/>
                  <p>But let all ſuch poor true hearted wretches be of good cheer. They that cannot reckon for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, God ſhall reckon for them, and help them to make it out. The Spirit within them ſhall cry <hi>Abba</hi> Father for them, and help them in all their infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with ſighes and groans which they cannot utter. Chriſt doth plead for their Right in Heaven, which he hath obtained for them; and knows how to have compaſſion upon the ignorant, and them that are out of the way, for that he himſelf alſo was one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed with infirmities.</p>
                  <p>As a faithful and kind Steward will reckon to a poor ſervant his dues to a farthing,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.2.</note> when he cannot reckon for himſelf: So will Chriſt do for theſe poor Creatures, and all that are Chriſts faithful Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and diſpenſers of the myſteries of Salvation.</p>
                  <p>The fault is in the falſe Teachers, that fright poor Souls with Hell and Damnation, Phyſicians of no value, miſerable Comforters, ſuch as cannot, or will not ſhew unto man his Righteouſneſs, nor ſave a Soul from the Pit. They are of ſuch evil Natures, and ſo full of ſpiritual Pride and Malice, that they will neither enter into Heaven themſelves, nor ſuffer others that would, by their good will. Such whoſe Eye is evil, becauſe Gods is good, and would fain have others to be in no better condition then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Some make a true accompt, and are able to prove it, being ſtrong in the Faith,<note place="margin">Chap. 17. <hi>Demonſtration.</hi>
                     </note> nothing doubting.</p>
                  <p>They Demonſtrate their Aſſurance thus.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The Cauſe of Salvation is Gods Promiſe.</item>
                     <item>2. The Effect is Salvation its ſelf.</item>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:93356:32"/>
                     <item>3. The means that makes the Cauſe to produce this effect, is their own Faith.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>So in <hi>Logick.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Concluſion is the effect of two Propoſitions rightly figured; whereof one is the Cauſe, and the other is the Medium or Mean between the Cauſe and the effect. The major Term in the major Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is the Cauſe. The minor Term in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor Propoſition is the Effect: And the Medium or middle Term, in both major and minor Propoſition, is the Means that produceth the Effect in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion: As thus.</p>
                  <p>A living Creature is Senſible.</p>
                  <p>A man is a living Creature, Therefore A man is Senſible.</p>
                  <p>This laſt Propoſition is the Effect of the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; in which Senſibility, which is the Major Term, is the Cauſe, and a man is the Effect. And a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Creature is the Means, whereby this Cauſe produceth this Effect. For, Becauſe man is a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Creature, Therefore he is Senſible.</p>
                  <p>So in <hi>Logiſtick.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Power or Product is the Effect of two Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers rightly multiplyed, when one of thoſe two is the root of that Power, and the other is the Rate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Root and the Power.</p>
                  <p>As 6 is the Cauſe of 12, 12 is the Effect; and the Multiplication of the Root 2 is the Means between the Cauſe and the Effect. So Promiſes are the Cauſe of Bleſſedneſs is the Effect; and Faith is the Means, between the Cauſe and the Effect.</p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:93356:32"/>
                  <p>The ground of both theſe Reaſonings and Recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings is this.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Thoſe things that agree in one Third, do agree among themſelves; as in <hi>Logick,</hi> As the Major and Minor agree in the Medium, therefore they agree among themſelves.</p>
                  <p>So in Logiſtick. The Multiplicand and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct agree in the Root by the means of the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication by that Root, As 6 and 12 agree together in the Root 2. by the means of the Rate or Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication: by the Root 2. And into which they are reſolved. So Gods Promiſes, and our Salvation do agree in Faith.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whatſoever is affirmed of the <hi>Genus,</hi> is affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med alſo of the Species, and all that are under it. As whatſoever is affirmed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Father of the Faithful, is affirmed of all the Faithful, the children of <hi>Abraham.</hi> Bleſſedneſs is affirmed of <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.9.</note> Therefore Bleſſedneſs is affirmed of all the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of faithfull <hi>Abraham.</hi> —<hi>So then, All that believe, are Bleſſed with faithful</hi> Abraham.</p>
                  <p>This is all the aſſurance that can be had, and this is enough by all Reaſon, to a reaſonable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from a Reaſonable God, that reaſons with us according to our capacities as reaſonable Creatures.</p>
                  <p>As for Revelations and Inſpirations, we may not expect them. For God will have us to live here by Faith, and not by Sight or Senſe, that muſt be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
                  <p>Therefore, though I ſee, or feel no comfort;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap. 18.</hi> Faith above Hope.</note> yet I have Faith, and live thereby. Though I be in the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:93356:33"/>Dark, and lie low in the Dungeon, and ſtick faſt in the Mire and Clay, and the Waters flow over me, and the weeds of Deſpair are wrapped about my head, being gone down to the bottoms of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and the Earth with her Barrs are round about me for ever; ſo that I ſay in the Judgment of my weak fleſh, I am loſt, I have no hopes: Yea, though beſides all this, to keep me down the more, that I may be ſure never to riſe into any hopeful or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable condition, I ſee nothing but miſery about me, and feel it in my own perſon; and hear nothing but Scorns, Reproaches, and Condemnations; yet I believe ſtill. I hold my own. My houſe is built upon a Rock. I keep me cloſe unto my God. I ſtrengthen my ſelf in him. I ſee all, and hear all, and bear all, and ſay nothing.</p>
                  <p>I am prompted often to renounce all hope, and to curſe God and die in deteſtation of the failings of his Promiſes, becauſe he hath mocked me. And that I might not be altogether miſerable here, I am bidden to Eat and Drink, for to morrow I ſhall Die. To enjoy the good things that are preſent, and ſpeedily uſe the Creatures as in Youth. To fill my ſelf with coſtly Wine and Ointments,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 2.6.</note> and let no Flowr of the Spring paſs by me. To crown my ſelf with Roſe-buds, before they be withered; not to go without my part of voluptuouſneſs, but to leave tokens of joyfulneſs in every place, for this is my Portion and Lot. For our Time is a very ſhadow that paſſeth away, and after our end there in no returning; for it is faſt ſealed, that no man cometh
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:93356:33"/>again. We are all but of yeſterday, and to morrow we ſhall not be.</p>
                  <p>All this I hear, but give no conſent; I am content to lie ſtill in ſilence, though it be without comfort, and wait upon my God; and reſolve, that though he kill me, yet I will put my truſt in him.</p>
                  <p>And this is Faith to believe above Hope, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Hope.</p>
                  <p>I ſpeak nothing all this while to Hypocrites, for their hope ſhall periſh. Hypocriſy cannot conſiſt with faithfulneſs, it makes ſhipwrack of Faith, and of a good Conſcience. The Lake that burneth with Fire and Brimſtone, is the portion of Hypocrites, even the ſame that was provided for the Devil and his Angels, and for all them that make and love lies.</p>
                  <p>I ſpeak nothing to profane Perſons &amp; Atheiſts, for theſe have condemned themſelves.</p>
                  <p>But I ſpeak to the plain True-hearted Believers, That between God and their own Conſciences, they ſhould fear nothing if their cauſe be good.</p>
                  <p>This takes off all Diſputes, about the Church,<note place="margin">Chap. 19. <hi>Diſputes.</hi>
                     </note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Baptiſme, the Lords Supper, Faith, Juſtification, Merits, Infallibility, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We may all comply very well, if we hold the ſame Faith in the prime neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Principles which are but few. There needs no hatred or ſtrangeneſs to condemn or divide about Circumſtances and Superſtructures, ſo long as we do all agree in Fundamentals.</p>
                  <p>And as for Ceremonies and Forms of outward worſhip, the Law is a Rule to every mans Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:93356:34"/>and this is the ſafeſt way to fulfil all Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: But it is not ſafe to Divide, or Rebel, either in the Church or State; for that overthrows the unity of the Faith, and the bond of Peace.</p>
                  <p>This takes off all blame in God,<note place="margin">Chap. 20. <hi>Excuſes.</hi>
                     </note> and all excuſes from our ſelves, and puts every man into a hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful capacity of Salvation.</p>
                  <p>For if we be not juſtified to Salvation, it is not Gods fault, but our own; becauſe we do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</p>
                  <p>God hath graciouſly promiſed, but man hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graciouſly refuſed and rejected Gods kindneſs, and man hath nothing to ſay for himſelf. Let God be true, but let every man be a Lye. Our deſtruction is from our ſelves, but in God is our help.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4.</note> —<hi>But if our Goſpel be hid, it is hid to them that are loſt, In whom the God of this World hath blinded the minds of men which believe not, leaſt the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt who is the Image of God, ſhould ſhine unto them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:93356:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>2 COR. 5.7.</hi> For we walk by Faith, not by ſight.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>INTRODUCTION.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Aith, that is the evidence of things not ſeen, abſtracts the Soul from ſenſe.</p>
                  <p>Therefore as that Faith that is ſo abſtracted from ſenſe, is counted to us for Righteouſneſs, or doth juſtifie us to Eternal life: So the ſame Faith kept by works, upholds us in our Juſtification, and makes us to walk before God, in the Practiſe of a ſpiritual life, abſtracted from all carnal and ſenſual wayes, which is our Sanctification.</p>
                  <p>For as the end is Spiritual that we aime at, and not Carnal: So the means whereby we attain to this End, are Spiritual, and not Carnal, that is Faith, and the life of Faith, not of Sight.</p>
                  <p>For the Juſt man lives by his Faith, and not by his ſight or ſenſe; and does not make haſt, but waits patiently for the Hope of Glory that ſhall be revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: Still looking beyond this life, and forgetting theſe things which are here behind, reacheth out, and preſſeth hard to the mark of the High Calling, which is laid up for him in Chriſt Jeſus.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.24, 25.</note> 
                     <hi>For we are ſaved by Hope, but hope that is ſeen is not Hope; for what a man ſeeth, why doth he yet hope for? but if we hope for that we ſee not, then do we with
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:93356:35"/>patience wait for it.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1.</note> —<hi>Faith is the ſubſtance of things hoped for, the evidence of things not ſeen. When I was a Child, I ſpake as a Child, I underſtood as a Child, I thought as a Child; but when I became a man, I put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way childiſh things.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> 13.10, 11.</note> 
                     <hi>For we now ſee through a glaſs darkly, but then face to face. Now I know in part, but then ſhall know, even as alſo I am known.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Subject is Walking or Living.</p>
                  <p>The Parts are Faith, Sight, or a Spiritual and a Carnal Life.</p>
                  <p>The Doctrine.<note place="margin">Chap. 1. <hi>Life.</hi>
                     </note> A Chriſtians Life is Spiritual.</p>
                  <p>Life is,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Of Nature, Pure, Harmleſs, as of other living Creatures.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Of ſenſe, irregular, ſinful, brutiſh, irrational, Earthly.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Moral by practiſe of Virtue.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Civil, in Society, Juſtice, under Laws.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Spiritual, Self-denying, above Laws. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chriſtians by their Spiritual lives,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.19.</note> come up higher then the Laws. —<hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then ſerveth the Law? it was added becauſe of Tranſgreſſions, 'till the ſeed ſhould come, to whom the Promiſe was made.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15.</note> —<hi>The ſpiritual man judgeth all things, but he himſelf is judged of no man.</hi>—<hi>The Law is good if a man uſe it lawfully.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> 
                     <hi>Knowing this, that the Law is not made for a Righteous man, but for the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and Diſobedient, for the ungodly and ſinners, for wholy and profane, for murderers of fathers, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deres of mothers, for man-ſlayers, for whoremongers, for them that defile themſelves with mankind, for men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtealers,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:93356:35"/>for liars, for perjured perſons, and if there be any other thing that is contrary to ſound Doctrine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the glorious Goſpel of the bleſſed God commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to my truſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This life Sanctifies and ſpiritualizeth Nature, Senſe, Manners, and Laws. <hi>For though we walk after the fleſh.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>we do not war after the fleſh. For the weapons of our war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare are not carnal, but mighty through God, for the pulling down of ſtrong holds, caſting down imaginations, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very high thing that exalteth its ſelf againſt the knowledg of God, and bringing into captivity every thought to the obedience of Chriſt.</hi> —<hi>We are delivered from the Law,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.6.</note> 
                     <hi>that being dead wherein we were held, that we ſhould ſerve in newneſs of ſpirit, and not in the oldneſs of the letter.</hi> —<hi>Let not ſin reign therefore in your mortal bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.12.13.</note> 
                     <hi>that ye ſhould obey it in the luſts thereof. Neither yeild ye your members as inſtruments of unrighteouſneſs unto ſin, but yield your ſelves to God as thoſe that are alive from the dead, and your members as inſtruments of righteouſneſs unto God; for ſin ſhall not have do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over you, for ye are not under the Law, but under Grace.</hi> —<hi>Knowing this,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.6.</note> 
                     <hi>that our old man is Crucified with him, that the body of ſin might be deſtroyed, that from henceforth we ſhould not ſerve ſin.</hi> —<hi>I am Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified with Chriſt, nevertheleſs I live; yet not I, but Chriſt liveth in me, and the life which I now live in the fleſh,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.10.</note> 
                     <hi>I live by the faith of the Son of God, who loved me, and gave himſelf for me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that this life is High.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Above all natural ſenſual pleaſures, profits, Honors, Arts, Powers, Glories, Liberties, Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:93356:36"/>Friends, Health, Strength, Peace, Orders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Above all natural ſenſual Pains, Wants, Shames, Ignorances, Weakneſſes, Diſgraces, Defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, Enemies, Diſeaſes, Warres, Slaveries, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that I value the Pleaſures of God, and the profit of Eternal Life, and the honour of being the child of God, and the knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus, and the Power of God, and the Glory of Heaven, and the Liberty of the Goſpel, and the Beauty of Grace, and the Friendſhip of God, and of Saints and Angels, and the Health, and Peace of my Soul, infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely above all the Pleaſures, Profits, Honors, Arts, Powers, Glories, and all the Pains, and Wants, the Shames, Ignorances, and weakneſſes, and all the miſeries of this life.— <hi>I glory in tribulations, and chuſe rather to ſuffer afflictions with the people of God, then to enjoy the Pleaſures of ſin which are but for a ſeaſon.—For whoſoever is born of God overcometh the World,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.4, 5.</note> 
                     <hi>and this is the victory that overcometh the World, even our Faith; who is he that overcometh the World, but he hath believeth that Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9.</note> —<hi>Whoſoever is born of God doth not commit ſin, for his ſeed remaineth in him, and he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſin, becauſe he is born of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. This life regulates all Paſſions, Love, Hatred, Joy, Grief, Hope, Deſpair, Boldneſs, Fear, Anger, Revenge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and raiſes them to Coeleſtial Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. This Life ſublimates all Faculties, Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, Will, Memory, Conſcience.</p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:93356:36"/>
                  <p n="5">5. This Life attains to true Wiſdome and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of Spirit.</p>
                  <p>By Exemption from vulgar Errors,<note place="margin">Chap. 2. <hi>Vulgar Errors.</hi>
                     </note> Vices and Paſſions. <hi>Lata eſt ad mortem via, Alienis perimus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplis. Odi profanum vulgus &amp; arceo.</hi> Broad is the way that leadeth to Death. We periſh if we follow evil examples. I hate the profane Rout, and all their cuſtomes of Swearing, Lying, Stealing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and tend towards a harmony of rational Judgment and will, with ſenſual Apprehenſion, and Deſire.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By univerſal liberty of ſpirit in Judgment and Will.<note place="margin">Chap. 3. <hi>Liberty.</hi>
                     </note> The judgment of a Wiſe-man trieth all things, yet is not tied to any thing; is open and free, yet captivates its underſtanding to the obedience of Faith. —<hi>The ſpiritual man judgeth all things,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>or.</hi> 2.15.</note> 
                     <hi>but he himſelf is judged of no man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Many are deceived by approving and following cuſtomes, becauſe they are in credit and uſe, without examination.</p>
                  <p>We may and muſt live in obedience to laws,<note place="margin">Chap. 4. <hi>Obedience.</hi>
                     </note> and Cuſtomes; ſpeak and do as the Vulgar, but not Judge as they do, but rather judge them. Powers and Laws, and Cuſtomes, may govern my hand, and my tongue, leaſt I diſturb the peace of the World, but not my Spirit: my outward, but not my inward man.</p>
                  <p>Behold I ſhew you a more excellent way,<note place="margin">Chap. 5. <hi>Dogmatiſts.</hi>
                     </note> not to be Dogmatical or Magiſterial in Proud Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, or Definitions. <hi>Scimus nihil: opinamur veriſimilia: fingunt docti magis quam nôrint.</hi> We know little: we gueſs at the moſt likely things:
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:93356:37"/>learned Men, fancy more then they know. There is a vain Philoſophy and oppoſitions of Sciences, falſly ſo call'd by men that are vainly pufft up with their fleſhly minds, and ſuch as dote about Queſtions, not knowing whereof they ſpake, nor whereof they do affirm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Plato</hi> never intended to tye us to his <hi>Idaea's,</hi> nor <hi>Pythagoras</hi> to his <hi>Numbers,</hi> nor <hi>Epicurus</hi> to his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms;</hi> they only abounded in their own ſenſe to themſelves, and the ſolacing of their own ſpirits with their own Notions. Dogmatiſts are moſt Pedan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick. <hi>Socrates</hi> was far from them, and was therefore counted the Wiſeſt man. <hi>Cogitationes mortalium timidae, incertae ſunt inventiones noſtrae.</hi> The thoughts of Mortals are fearful, and our Inventions uncertain. God knows the thoughts of Man, that they are but vain.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.2.</note>—<hi>If any man thinketh that he knoweth any thing, he knoweth nothing as he ought to know.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Who can obtrude Principles upon the World, but God himſelf, who only is to be believed? Let the obtruders of Principles agree in them if they can, and then I ſhall ſubmit.</p>
                  <p>—<hi>Purge out therefore the old Leaven, that ye may become a new Lump.—Put off the old man, and put on the new man.</hi> Be as white Paper, fit to receive fair Impreſſion. Be biaſſed no way, but reſpect the Truth equally; As new born Babes receive the ſincere Milk of the Word, which is able to ſave your Soules.</p>
                  <p>Be <hi>Academicks,</hi> and <hi>Pyrrhonians;</hi> for men of that Temper are never Hereticks, Fanaticks, Opinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:93356:37"/>Troublers of the World, as Dogmatiſts Pedan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, Magiſterial and Definitive Gnoſticks. <hi>O ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines ad ſervitutem nati!</hi> A generation of Men born to continual Thraldome, and will not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed.</p>
                  <p>Like them Men in <hi>Plato</hi>'s Cave, that never had knowledge but of Shadows; and if they be told of the Beauty of the Subſtances, they will not believe it: And if any offer to drag them out of the Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon to behold the fair Glory of the Sun, and the Truth of all things diſcovered by the light thereof, they will ſhut their eyes, and ſtrive to run back to their old darkneſs again. In Love with bondage. Violent, not hearkning to any thing wiſer then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: <hi>Malè cuncta miniſtrat impetus. Feſtina lente.</hi> All haſte makes waſte. It is good to <hi>try all things,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.21.</note> 
                     <hi>and hold faſt that which is good. —Whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are honeſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8.</note> 
                     <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever things are juſt, whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things are lovely, whatſoever things are of good report, if there be any virtue, and if there be any praiſe, think on theſe things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. By true eſſential ſimple Honeſty,<note place="margin">Chap. 6. <hi>Honeſty.</hi>
                     </note> and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Spirit. A true, manly, generous, free, cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, equal, pliable Genius. A ſpirit freely good, not for fear of Puniſhment, or hope of Reward.</p>
                  <p>Not only natural Innocency and goodneſs, not acquired virtue and honeſty: but High and ſtately Reſolutions of Grace and Perfection, more then Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Art, or Law require.—<hi>Covet after the beſt things, and yet I ſhew you a more excellent way.</hi> And this
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:93356:38"/>Temper of down right ſimplicity, and well meaning, is the <hi>Mercury</hi> that points juſtly to the High-way of Grace and Glory.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Stoicks</hi> aimed at this Diſpoſition, and <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures</hi> more (witneſs <hi>Seneca,</hi> though blaſted by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of unequal Credit) to be above Want, Pain, Grief, Joy, Shame, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſurely they were not all ſullen, and moroſe; but very firme, grave, ſevere, as <hi>Cato</hi> was, and pleaſant too.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. By Practicing true Piety.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap. 7.</hi> Piety and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>An opinion contrary to this, prevailes in the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal World. As</p>
                  <p>That God is appeaſed with ſatisfactions of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, moved with Gifts and offerings, Delighted with the Torments and Ruins of his poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, with the Sacrifices of innocent Beaſts, and ſometimes men, as preſents to appeaſe his Wrath; affected with Auſterities, Sack-cloth, and Hair-ſhirts, Aſhes, and hard cold Stones, Macerated bodies, Wan-looks, Whining or Yelling noiſes, Cuttings, Launcings, Pilgrimages, Incenſe, Candles, Holy-waters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as are practiced in Hermitages, and Cells.</p>
                  <p>A madneſs to flatter the Divinity with Inhuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. To think to ſatisfy Gods Juſtice with Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty.</p>
                  <p>Of what nature do they judge God to be? Surely they think him ſuch a one as themſelves. And who hath required theſe things at their hands?</p>
                  <p>Is God delighted, or ever was, or ever will be, with burnt Sacrifices, with Calves of a yeer old, with Rivers
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:93356:38"/>of Oil, or the Cattel upon a thouſand Hills? or with the fruit of the Body for the ſin of the Soul? God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him truely, muſt worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth.</p>
                  <p>The moſt noble ſervice of God, is without too much External, and Carnal ſervice. It draws the Soul into its ſelf, and raiſes it by pure contemplation to a Heavenly worſhip.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>—Si Deus eſt Animus, nobis ut carmina dicunt,</l>
                     <l>Hic tibi praecipuè ſit purâ mente colendus.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>It was the humour of the <hi>Jewes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap. 8.</hi> Judaiſme and Heatheniſme.</note> that knew no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to dote upon a Material Temple, and cry out <hi>The Temple of the Lord, The Temple of the Lord,</hi> to be raviſhed with numerous, laborious, and coſtly Ceremonies, and the Purer ſort to ſuperadd of their own Inventions, innumerable Traditions, impoſed equally to be obſerved with thoſe that God had commanded; yea more. Thus their Religion exu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berated into theſe excreſcencies and formalities, which deſtroyed the Power of Godlineſs.</p>
                  <p>God gave them a Carnal Commandment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it fitted their low Eſtate, and he kept them buſied with many chargeable ſervices to pleaſe them as children, with outward performances, ſemblable to the Heathen worſhip, and to keep them buſy from doing the ſame Devotions to the Idol Gods, to which he knew they had a great wambling: But with theſe ſervices God was never fully pleaſed. He intended farre higher Duties, unto which he led them by the hand, if they had had the wit to obſerve
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:93356:39"/>it, according as the Prophets did often hint unto them. But they reſted in the Letter, and in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke-daies, and would not underſtand what God far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intended; no not when they were ſorely ſlaſht in the Babiloniſh Captivity; nor in the time of the <hi>Maccabees;</hi> nor under the ſore Yoke of <hi>Antiochus,</hi> nor yet of the <hi>Romans,</hi> when the Goſpel began to dawn; nor yet in the dayes of Chriſt himſelf, and his Apoſtles, when the cleer day-ſpring from an high did viſit them, and that God did fully reveal what worſhip he meant ſhould continue for ever; and that all their rude and beggarly elements ſhould be laid aſide, as being added only becauſe of Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, till the Promiſed Seed ſhould come. —<hi>It was therefore neceſſary, that the Patterns of things in the Heavens ſhould be purified with theſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.23.</note> 
                     <hi>but the heavenly things themſelves with better Sacrifices then theſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But ſtill they ſtumbled at the Old ſtumbling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of a Temporal Covenant, eſtabliſhed upon Temporal Promiſes, and commanding Temporal Services.</p>
                  <p>And from hence many Chriſtians firſt taken from the Nation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and afterwards from all the Heathen Countries, have erred exceedingly; Partly by mixing <hi>Judaiſme;</hi> and partly by mixing Paganiſme, with Chriſtianity, which both of them are not out of us unto this very day, although the Apoſtles made it their buſineſs, as they had then too much occaſion, to overthrow theſe two maine er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, from whence all other Hereſies have been deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:93356:39"/>and that Chriſt himſelf did ſo much ſpeak againſt the continuance of the Jewiſh way, and the Introduction of Heatheniſh cuſtoms, by Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching a more Spiritual Law, and declaring Eternal Promiſes.</p>
                  <p>All though God hath winked at the Nonage of the Jews, and the Ignorance of the Gentiles;<note place="margin">Chap. 9. <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>aniſme.</hi>
                     </note> yet now God will have all men every where to aſpire to perfection, and learn better things, commanded in a better Covenant, that is eſtabliſhed upon better Promiſes; eſpecially in the dayes of Adverſity, when we are pinched with long and ſore Warrs, with plagues of Fire and Water, and ſundry kinds of Death.</p>
                  <p>It is high time now for the World to grow wiſer, to come off from the Vanities and Pomps of this Life, and walk highly with God in the Spiritual Exerciſe of Faith and Repentance.</p>
                  <p>Away then with this Looſe and Carnal way of Living: This will not do. The Goſpel calls for higher things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. This Looſe and Carnal Life, will never ſatisfy the Conſcience, nor pleaſe God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This formal and outward Worſhip will not ſerve the Turne.</p>
                  <p>You muſt come up to the pure Goſpel-way, to the life of Faith, and to the worſhip of the ſpirit, or you can never pleaſe God.</p>
                  <p>Be honeſt and juſt in your words and Actions.</p>
                  <p>Be dutiful and obedient to the Laws.</p>
                  <p>Be decent and orderly in Gods Worſhip.</p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:93356:40"/>
                  <p>But ſtill I ſhew you a more excellent way. This is to be done, and you are not to leave the other undone. For thus it becometh us after Chriſts own Example, <hi>To fulfil all Rigteouſneſs;</hi> To offend none, but to <hi>give unto</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things which are</hi> Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars, <hi>and unto God the things which are Gods.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>APPLICATION.</head>
                  <p>I have ſet before you two wayes, Faith and Sight; Spirit and Fleſh: chooſe therefore the better part, that ſhall never be taken away from you.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Cheriſh the life of Nature, by Temperance, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, and Chaſtity.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Regulate the life of ſenſe, by Reaſon, Prudence, and Moderation.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Order the Moral life, by Virtue, Juſtice, Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and Honeſty.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Maintain the Civil Life, by dutiful ſubmiſſion to Rulers, and their Laws for the publike Good.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Keep the Spiritual Life above all by Faith:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Which may Sanctify Nature, Senſe, Morality, and Laws.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Which may tranſcend all carnal Profits, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, Honours, Arts, Powers, Glories, Liberties, Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Friends, Health, Peace, Orders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Which may overcome all Carnal Pains, Wants, Shames, Ignorances, Weakneſſes, Diſgraces, Defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, Enemies, Diſeaſes, Warrs, Bondage, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Which may regulate all Paſſions, of Love, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, Hope, Deſpair, Joy, Grief, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:93356:40"/>
                  <p n="5">5. Which may ſublimate all Faculties, Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, Will, Memory, Conſcience.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Which may arrive at the height of true Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Peace and Tranquility of Minde.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. By exemption from vulgar Errors, Vices, and Paſſions.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By aiming at Univerſal Liberty in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Will, ſtill ſubmitting to Faith.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. By learning true eſſential ſimple honeſty, and plainneſs of Spirit.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. By Practicing true Piety.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Free from Jewiſh worſhip.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Free from Heatheniſh Idolatry.</p>
                  <p>This is the high and noble way of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Jeſus Chriſt, which is of the ſpirit that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth life: not of the Letter that killeth.</p>
                  <p>Thus we overcome ſin from ruling in our mortal Bodies, that we ſhould be obedient unto the luſts thereof.</p>
                  <p>Thus we overcome the Temptations, and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the World.</p>
                  <p>Thus we overcome the Devil, and bruiſe Satan under every one of our Feet, and through Jeſus Chriſt are more then Conquerors. <hi>And thanks be to God which giveth us this victory through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Look therefore on things Spiritual and not on things Carnal:<note place="margin">Chap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0. <hi>Faith.</hi>
                     </note> on things Eternal, and not on things Temporal.—<hi>For the things that are ſeen, are tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and carnal; but the things which are not ſeen but believed are Spiritual and Eternal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:93356:41"/>
                  <p>Believe your ſins are blotted out of Gods Book (for ſo they are when forſaken) Though you cannot ſee your Pardon ſealed by Gods ſpirit, by your ſenſe; yet by your Faith you may ſee it.</p>
                  <p>Believe the Peace of God &amp; of your own Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; though the ſenſe diſcern it not: yet your faith may.</p>
                  <p>Believe the Judgments of God are eſcaped, and ſhall not hurt you; though you feel preſent pain in the Fleſh, as is needful for you.</p>
                  <p>Believe the Devil is overcome; though he ſift you as the wheat is ſifted: yet Chriſt hath prayed for you, that your Faith ſhall not fail you, and his Grace ſhall be ſufficient for you.</p>
                  <p>Believe you ſhall live, though you die and ſee corruption; for you ſhall die in Faith.</p>
                  <p>This is Faith, to believe above ſenſe, above hope, and contrary to hope, &amp; the judgment of fleſh and bloud.</p>
                  <p>This is Faith, To be preſent with God in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, though you be abſent from him in the Fleſh.</p>
                  <p>This is Faith, to rejoice in Miſery, to glory in Tribulations, to be raviſhed with Spiritual comforts, during the enjoyment of Temporal, To find Reſt in God in the midſt of Trouble, to reſt upon Gods Promiſes of Pardon and Bleſſedneſs in the midſt of Sins and Miſeries.</p>
                  <p>I will believe, though I ſee not, nor feel not any comfor: This ſhall be my joy &amp; comfort in believing.</p>
                  <p>I will believe, though I can give no Definition nor Reaſon for my Faith.</p>
                  <p>I will live in the Spirit, though I live in the Fleſh; for I do not live after the Fleſh.</p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:93356:41"/>
                  <p>I will worſhip God in the Spirit, though I uſe a Forme and outward Ceremony.</p>
                  <p>I will Eat and Drink, and be merry in the Lord.</p>
                  <p>I will ſuffer patiently in the Lord.</p>
                  <p>I will Live and Die in the Lord.</p>
                  <p>Tell me not of Temptations, I know who is on my ſide, and will deliver me.</p>
                  <p>Tell me not of Tribulations, I know who will Save me.</p>
                  <p>Tell me not of Death and Hell, I know who will Redeem me.</p>
                  <p>Yea; He hath Delivered, He hath ſaved, He hath Redeemed me already.</p>
                  <p>The Forgiveneſs of my Sins paſt, preſent, and to come, is already preſent with me.</p>
                  <p>The Deliverance from all my Sufferings is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy preſent with me.</p>
                  <p>Eternal Life and Salvation is already preſent with me.</p>
                  <p>I know in whom I have Truſted. Here will I fix, ſay the World, the Fleſh or the Divel, what they will or can.</p>
                  <p>But with a Carnal Life,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap. 11.</hi> Carnal m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> this Faith and Hope can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conſiſt.</p>
                  <p>Of all Tempers, theſe are moſt oppoſite to Faith.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Outward uncleanneſs, Rioting and Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Chambering and Wantonneſs, Strife and Envy, Curſing, Damning, Oppreſſion and Cruelty, and ſuch like.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Inward Hypocriſy, Lying and Cheating, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:93356:42"/>
                  <p n="3">3. Open Rebellion, Sacriledge, Sedition and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring, and ſuch like.</p>
                  <p>—<hi>The Carnal mind underſtandeth not the things of God; neither indeed can it, becauſe they are ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally diſcerned.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus it becometh us to Preach, and you to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, Grace, Faith, Repentance, Patience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is too Legal, to preach Laws, Duties, Curſes, Threatnings, Damnation.</p>
                  <p>The Goſpel is, Faith, Love, Hope, Joy in the Holy Ghoſt; <hi>Grace, mercy, pace from God our Father, and from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Till we perſwade you to Faith, we ſhall never do our work, nor your work for you.</p>
                  <p>Believe only and you ſhall be ſaved, This will bring works, and duties, and mortifications, and all ſhall be pleaſing to God, and without this, nothing ſhall be pleaſing unto him, <hi>for without Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Say not; You cannot underſtand this Spiritual Doctrine of the Goſpel; and this Rule is too high for you to walk by; it is too hard a Taske to lead this life of Faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                     </label> I anſwer:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap. 12.</hi> Goſpel Eaſy.</note> It is eaſy to underſtand this Doctrine; and he that is willing, ſhall be made to know the mind of God, and to do the ſame.</p>
                  <p>It is as eaſy to underſtand this Goſpel-Precept, <hi>Thou ſhalt not Luſt,</hi> or <hi>Hate,</hi> as to underſtand this Legal Command, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery;</hi> or <hi>Thou ſhalt not Kill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:93356:42"/>
                  <p>It is as eaſy to underſtand, That the thoughts of the Heart, and the deſires of the Will, are to be regulated, as the words of the Tongue, or the works of the Hand.</p>
                  <p>It is as eaſy to underſtand Faith as Works, to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve as to Live, To accept of the Covenant of Grace as of works.</p>
                  <p>As for the Myſteries of Faith in the Trinity, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, Deſcenſion, Interceſſion of Chriſt, and ſuch like. They are more eaſily and ſafely to be believed, then diſputed. And the ſpirit is given to all that Believe, that they might underſtand, and do the Will of God. That they might know the heighth, and length, and breadth, and depth of the Love of God which paſſeth all knowledg.</p>
                  <p>It is as eaſy and farre more, to hear of Grace, Mercy, and Peace; as to hear of Law, Curſes, and Damnation.</p>
                  <p>It is as eaſy to hope as fear, to rejoyce as to mourn, to be free as to be ſlaves, to walk in light as in darkneſs, To underſtand the good of the Soul as of the Body, the life to come as this life preſent.</p>
                  <p>Wiſe are we to know this World, Gain, Honor, pleaſure, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and wiſer we might be to know the World to come.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob: </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>Ob.</hi> A hard ſaying, who can hear it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>Sol.</hi> An eaſy and true ſaying, and very pleaſant, and may be heard. Yea, and <hi>he that hath Ears to hear, let him hear;</hi> for he may hear if he will: none ſo deaf as they that will not hear. The Charmer charmes often and wiſely, unleſs we ſtop our Ears
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:93356:43"/>with the deaf Adder, and refuſe to hear the voice of this Charmer, though he charms unto us, never ſo often, never ſo wiſely. There is a voice behind us, yea within us, which ſaies unto us, <hi>This is the way, walk in it:</hi> Turn from the ways of wickedneſs, paſs by them, and come not neer unto them, for fear iniquity be your Ruin; for why will ye Dye? O when will it once be!</p>
                  <p>The Sun of the Goſpel ſhines very cleerly; but the World ſhuts her eyes upon it. The <hi>light is come into the world, but men loved darkneſs rather then light, becauſe their deeds are evil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The oppoſers of this heavenly way of walking with God in Faith and ſpiritual Duties, are</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Outward Formaliſts and Will-worſhippers,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap. 13.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ormali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ts.</note> which reſt in the Letter, and in the outward work done; as in Faſts, Feaſts, Forms, Auſterities, Almes, Juſtice, Temperance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet there is a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent way to go on to perfection; — <hi>not to draw neer to God with our Lips, but our hearts:</hi> As the proud Phariſee that faſted twice in the Week, that made long Prayers, that paid Tithe of all that he poſſeſſed, that thanked God that he was not like other men; nor as that Publican: But the poor Publican went home to his houſe Juſtified rather then the other. And the very Publicans and Harlots ſhall enter into the Kingdome of Heaven by their Faith, when theſe Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites ſhall be ſhut out.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Law-Preachers,<note place="margin">Chap. 14. <hi>Law-Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</hi>
                     </note> and hearers of Curſes and Damnation. Are we Saved by the Works of the Law, or by the Faith of the Goſpel? By the works
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:93356:43"/>of the Law, no fleſh living ſhall be juſtified. What Law had the Heathens Preached unto them? They were never under the Law, they needed it not after they did believe, nor Wee. God did write in the Law in their hearts by his Spirit in the dayes of the Goſpel, and the Kingdome of Heaven is within us. The royal Law of Love, The perfect Law of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, is written upon the Tables of our hearts; and this is a ſufficient Rule to bring us to Heaven.</p>
                  <p>Mockers of Faith,<note place="margin">Chap. 15 <hi>Mockers.</hi>
                     </note> Self-denyal, Mortification, Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of heart, Poorneſs of Spirit, Mourning, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, hungring and thirſting after Righteouſneſs, Mercifulneſs, Peace-making, Suffering Perſecution, Rejoycing in Perſecution, which are the ſpiritual commands of Chriſt, to which Bleſſedneſs is promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Such Prophets as ſpeak of theſe things are counted Fools, and ſuch ſpiritual men eſteemed mad, by the voluptuous and Luxurious men of the World, and by the <hi>Zenonian</hi> Fataliſts, that depend upon ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Decrees, and put all to a venture.</p>
                  <p>What then remains, but that all Reaſonable men ſhould be ſatisfied with this reaſonable ſervice of Faith, which is above their Carnal Reaſon, but agreeable with all ſpiritual and Right Reaſon; and none but unreaſonable and abſurd men will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it.</p>
                  <p>I will reſolve therefore with my ſelf,<note place="margin">Chap. 16. <hi>Soul-Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                     </note> to go out of my ſelf, and truſt no longer in my Fleſh, nor in any Creature.</p>
                  <p>I will reſolve with my ſelf, to underſtand better things, and to know my ſelf more perfectly.</p>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:93356:44"/>
                  <p n="1">1. How all Sin is in my Fleſh.</p>
                  <p n="1">2. How all miſery is in my Fleſh.</p>
                  <p>And that this is but my outward Man, the old Man, That decayes and dies, which I am daily put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. How all Grace is in my Spirit.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. How all Glory is in my Spirit.</p>
                  <p>And that this is the Inward Man, The new Man, That quickens and lives, which I am daily put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on.</p>
                  <p>And that therefore by my Faith I live above ſin, and above Miſery, and beyond them both, while in my fleſh I am perplexed with them both.</p>
                  <p>What then is all this Mourning by reaſon of Sin, and for Afflictions here below?</p>
                  <p>Is not this the way to Heaven, though it be thus Rugged and Thorny? Is not this the Sea, and are not theſe the Waves, and Storms, and Rocks, and Quickſands that are therein?</p>
                  <p>But is not Chriſt my Pilot, and am I not ſafe under him? Have I not a ſure Guide, that will bring me into a ſafe Harbour? Can I not then have a little Patience? Tis but to have a little Patience.—</p>
                  <q>Dabit Deus his quoque finem.</q>
                  <p>'Tis but ſtanding ſtill a while, and I ſhall ſee the Salvation of God.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore then all this a do? Wherefore do ye trouble my Spirit? I am ready not only to ſuffer but to dye. There is no ſtrang thing happened unto me, but ſuch as is common to all the faithfull, and ſuch as happened to Chriſt himſelf.</p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:93356:44"/>
                  <p>What though I am Tempted, Afflicted, Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, I live ſtill. The juſt ſhall live by his Faith. My Veſſel is covered with Waves; yet ſhe bears up againſt them. My Houſe is beaten and ſhaken with winds and waves, yet it ſtands ſtill; becauſe it is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon a Rock.</p>
                  <p>I am fearful naturally, I do confeſs; yet by the Grace of God, I can look Sin, Miſery, and Death in the face, and truſt in God ſtill.</p>
                  <p>If I look only upon Sin, and Miſery, and Death, and Hell, alas I dye for fear: But if I look upon God and Chriſt, I live for evermore.</p>
                  <p>If I conſult with fleſh and bloud, I mourn and die: but if I conſult with the Spirit, I rejoyce and live. —<hi>They that live after the Fleſh, ſhall die: but they that by the ſpirit do mortify the deeds of the fleſh ſhall live.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Do we then live by Faith, or by Senſe? Spiritually, or Carnally?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> If we ſay we live by Faith, and by the Spirit, I ſay then, what means this lowing and bleating of the Beaſts that I hear?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde Luctus &amp; Planctus.</hi> Where is all this how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and Lamentation? Why all this Deſpairing and Doubting? O we of little Faith! <hi>A voice in</hi> Ramah <hi>is heard, bitter Lamentation,</hi> Rachel <hi>mourning for her children, and refuſeth to be comforted, becauſe they are not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But is Chriſts Church a Widdow, hath ſhe not a Husband? is ſhe an Orphan, and hath ſhe not a Father? Is ſhe a ſtranger, and hath ſhe not a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector?
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:93356:45"/>Surely ſhe is the Spouſe and Daughter of Chriſt and no ſtranger; therefore God will take care and charge of her, and do for her abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly above all that ſhe is able to aske or think. Doth God take care for Oxen, and for the Birds of the Air, and for the Lillies of the Field? and ſhall he not much more take care for us, O we of little Faith?</p>
                  <p>Let me alone therefore, and trouble me no more from henceforth, with idle Queſtions or direful Curſes. I have a God to truſt to. I have nothing to do with you, O ye ſubtil, O ye uncharitable ones! O my Soul ſtrengthen thou thy ſelf in thy God alone, it is good for me to wait upon my God, and to keep my ſelf cloſe to the Rock of my Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>Why, Have I not found his Goodneſs all along, and ſhould I doubt now? Have I ſerved ſo good a Maſter, and now ſhould I leave him?</p>
                  <p>Why, how, and by whom have I lived all this while under all ſorrows?</p>
                  <p>And how do I live ſtill?</p>
                  <p>And how do I hope to live hereafter?</p>
                  <p>And how do I hope to live for evermore? but by my Faith in Gods Promiſes.</p>
                  <p>I am not exactly Righteous, therefore I cannot live by my works, but I am willing to work Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and by the Grace of God I ſhall be accepted and live by Faith.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:93356:45"/>
                  <head>CONCLUSION.</head>
                  <p>The Doctrine of Faith is ſufficiently known, that thereby we are Juſtified, Regenerated, Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted, Incorporated into Chriſts Church, Elected, Sanctified, Aſſured, and ſhall be raiſed up from the dead, and live in glory everlaſtingly.</p>
                  <p>But who are the true Believers, is not ſo ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently known; and it is hard to know.</p>
                  <p>All will profeſs their Faith, but how do they prove it? All will reckon upon Salvation, but how do they prove their Reckoning?</p>
                  <p>Here lies the main Point, that men ſhould not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive themſelves.</p>
                  <p>Profeſſors enough, Teachers many; but how true God knows,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5.</note> and they themſelves do not know for want of Trial of themſelves.</p>
                  <p>Well therefore, ſaid the Apoſtle, <hi>Examine your ſelves, whither ye be in the Faith; prove your own ſelves, know ye not your own ſelves, how that Jeſus Chriſt is in you, except ye be Reprobates.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I take great care upon This.</p>
                  <p>I find high Pretenders to Faith, and to the Spirit,<note place="margin">Chap.17. <hi>Pretenders.</hi>
                     </note> and mighty zealots in all duties of Devotion; but I find alſo, that they are not honeſt, but Lyars, Chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Malicious, Proud, Boaſters, Rebellious, Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious, Extortioners, Lovers of themſelves, Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, Covetous, and the greateſt Troublers of the World. I do not ſay Swearers, nor open Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:93356:46"/>
                  <p>I wiſh theſe men to examine themſelves better, and know themſelves to be Hypocrites.</p>
                  <p>For God and the World know them ſo to be; for they daily rob God in Tithes, and offerings, and his Prieſts of honor and reſpect. They rob the King of Tributes and Cuſtomes, and of Honour and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
                  <p>They do cheat and forſwear to the ruin of their neighbours, none more.</p>
                  <p>Now ſhall ſuch a Faith ſave them? It muſt be no other then a dead Faith; Becauſe they are Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, and do no good works, therefore they have made ſhipwrack of a true Faith, and of a good Conſcience.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. I find ordinary Profeſſors of Faith, formal enough, Cuſtomary hearers and Worſhippers and juſt men: But they are not zealous, but they are not ſober and temperate, but they are curſers and ſwearers, I do not ſay they are Lyars.</p>
                  <p>I wiſh heartily theſe men would examine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves better; They are in a good way, and are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, but not all together good Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p>They are too luke-warm and formal. They muſt ſtir up themſelves more, or elſe they will come ſhort of true Faith.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. I find ſome that are cloſe and private, and make little open ſhew of any Religion to the World. Being no comers to Church, no Readers, nor Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers at home, regard no Laws nor Magiſtrates nor Miniſters: But keep to their ſhops and employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, greedily groveling upon the World and minding no divine Deity.</p>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:93356:46"/>
                  <p>I wiſh theſe men would examine themſelves bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and awaken out of their ſottiſh condition. For they can have no grounds to build any ſolid com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts to themſelves: but are as it were, without God in the World.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. I finde ſome that are open and profane Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Curſers, Swearers, Drunkards, Fighters, Revel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and ſlighters of all Religion, Laws, and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, unprofitable burdens of the Earth, conſumers of the precious things put forth by the Sun, and of the precious things put forth by the Moon; the enemies and ſhame of Mankind, and to their own Bodies and Souls.</p>
                  <p>I wiſh theſe men would better conſider, bethink themſelves, and examine in what a fearful and hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs condition they are in with God and Man.</p>
                  <p>For their Actions ſtink in the noſtrils of God, and he will blaſt them with the breath of his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; For there is no comfort nor ſafety in their Actions being inhumane and barbarous. A modeſt man that comes into their company, and hears their roarings, yellings, blaſphemies, and lewd ſpeeches, and ſees their antike Garbs and monſtrous beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, thinks himſelf in the Suburbs of Hell, or rather in the Court of <hi>Beelzebub.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore theſe men of all men, have the leaſt hopes of any reward in this World, or in the World to come. For if there be any Dignities, Offices, or Trades to manage, they are moſt unfit for them. Nor can the Gates of honor without great injury, lye open to theſe men, who defile their families, and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:93356:47"/>ſhame and undoe the Nation. And if there be any Reward in Heaven, they are ſure never to come there; and if there be none, they are unworthy to be rewarded here.</p>
                  <p>So that they are the very ſcum and droſs of the World; and it had been better for them if they had never been born, or been like the untimely fruit of a Woman, that had never ſeen the Sun.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>
                     </label> Who then are they that are in the Faith, or have Faith, or are in Chriſt, and no Reprobates.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> Onely they that work Righteouſneſs, and ſo ſhew their Faith by their Works, being truly honeſt and juſt to God and Men.</p>
                  <p>It is hard for the World to know a true Believer from a falſe; becauſe of Hypocriſy. A vizard and Diſguiſe of Religion, may cover black Deeds; fair Speeches, looks and actions, may almoſt deceive the very Elect.</p>
                  <p>But 'tis eaſy for a man to know himſelf, whither he be a Hypocrite or no, if he will but try. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4.</note> 
                     <hi>I know nothing by my ſelf.</hi> If there had been any thing he might have known it.—<hi>Thine own heart knoweth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.22.</note> 
                     <hi>that thou thy ſelf haſt curſed others. So thine own heart knoweth whither thou believeſt or diſſembleſt.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11.</note> 
                     <hi>—Who knoweth the things of a Man, ſave the ſpirit of man which is in him.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 2.44.</note> 
                     <hi>—The King ſaid to</hi> Shimei; <hi>Thou knoweſt all the wickedneſs, which thine heart is privy to.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                     </label> Say not as the vulgar do, to abuſe the Scripture and themſelves. —<hi>The heart of man is deceitful and Deſperately wicked,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.9.</note> 
                     <hi>and who can know it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:93356:47"/>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> I, who indeed beſides God and your ſelves? No man living can, you carry it ſo cunningly. It is an eaſy matter to cheat the World, but it is not ſo eaſy to cheat God, or your own conſciences. God is not a man that he ſhould be mocked, neither is he the ſon of man that he ſhould be deceived; and the conſcience is Gods vicegerent, a faithful Regiſter, a witneſs that will ſpeak the truth, the whole Truth, and nothing but the Truth, one day.</p>
                  <p>You need not therefore, be ignorant of your ſelves, nor cheat your ſelves unleſs you will.</p>
                  <p>You are willing to be deceived; therefore you are deceived; it is your own fault.</p>
                  <p>Never tell me you cannot tell your own heart, you may tell it well enough, if you would examine it. The Soul hath a faculty, not only to know, but to know what ſhe knows, and to reflect upon her own Actions.</p>
                  <p>I can tell I hope very well, whither I be honeſt or no; I, and no body elſe can tell but I, if I be cunning to hide diſhoneſty from them. But yet they may at laſt find me out, 'tis a thouſand to one elſe, if they live long enough by me, and try me much, and mark me well. There is nothing ſo ſecret, but at laſt it ſhall be revealed; and that which is done in Cloſets, ſhall be ſhewen upon the houſe tops.</p>
                  <p>What do men think that are Hypocrites?</p>
                  <p>Alas, it is a poor ſilly buſineſs.</p>
                  <p>If there be a God, as there is, he muſt know all; and if there ſhould chance to be a Heaven as there will be, they ſhall be ſure to be ſhut out. They had
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:93356:48"/>as good put off their vizard, and lay aſide their paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed veil, and ſpeak and do plainly, and be at open defiance with God, and never make mention of his name within their mouths; for their labour is in vain to Preach of him, and Pray to him, in whom they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve nothing at all.</p>
                  <p>The humour of theſe men is very ſtrange to take ſuch pains to no purpoſe at all.</p>
                  <p>Yea, but they have worldly ends thereby, to be counted Religious, that they get Riches and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
                  <p>Very well, then they have their Reward: but 'tis a poor one; yet it is ſuch as they like, much good it cannot do them, nay, much harm will accrue thereby.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. For God will condemne them much more.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Men will not love them, though they may fear them. Men count them as they are, falſe; and ſcorne them in their hearts for their baſeneſs.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They muſt ſhortly Dye, and then to what purpoſe is all this cloſeneſs, plotting and contriving to get a little Pelfe together, and to be revenged, and have their Wills; for ſhortly their Enemies, and thoſe they have oppreſſed, will dance upon their graves, their Names ſhall ſtink and rot; and their own ſeed, if not ſtrangers, throw away what they have unjuſtly gotten.</p>
                  <p>Is it not far better and ſafer to be plain and down right honeſt? And then</p>
                  <p>Amongſt good men a man ſhall be ſure to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and God will certainly reward him.</p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:93356:48"/>
                  <p>Beloved, bethink your ſelves, and be as you profeſs and ſeem to be.</p>
                  <p>Here are Sermons, Prayers, Communions, Bibles, and other good Books. What then? Will this do the work to uſe all theſe?</p>
                  <p>One thing is wanting, and then all is done. Hear Pray, Receive, Read, give Almes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in ſincerity, and humility.</p>
                  <p>What is it to be a great Talker of God; and with God, in Preaching, Praying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when the heart is not right with God all this while?</p>
                  <p>What is it to be a great Diſputer, and Contender for Religion, and the Ceremonies thereof, only to get applauſe and profit thereby?</p>
                  <p>What will all this availe at the hour of Death, or at the Day of Judgment?</p>
                  <p>At the hour of Death, they ſay, they care not; they muſt, and they can but dye.</p>
                  <p>At the day of Judgment, they paſs not for that; for they believe no ſuch thing. Let them but alone till that Day, and they ſhall do well enough, they will venture that.</p>
                  <p>Well then, if it be ſo; let them go as they are, and Gods Vengeance will go along with them; and for ever, deſpair of Gods Mercies: Let them enjoy this World, no wiſe man will envy them.</p>
                  <p>They are left to themſelves. They that are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, let them be wilful ſtill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob: </seg>
                     </label> Many ſay, they know no better.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                     </label> There are many things they might know, if they had a mind to know: but theſe men revel away all
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:93356:49"/>their Time, and never regard to know any thing that is good.</p>
                  <p>Who can pretend ignorance, that there is a God? and that he ſhould do as he would be done by? Not one: For theſe are Common Principles.</p>
                  <p>And as for Conſequences, men might eaſily make them, if they would take the pains, upon ſeveral occaſions in life. As to ſay, when they diſſemble, How do I look when I Lye? Do I not hide falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood under my Tongue, and is there not a Lie in my right hand? Do I ſpend vaſt Sums upon vanity of Apparel and Riotous living, and ſhould I grutch to pay the Miniſter his ſmall dues, or to give a little to the Poor. No man but might ſay and do theſe things, and ſuch as theſe, whenſoever occaſion is offered in his buſineſs amongſt men: But men ſleep or Pot away their dayes, and forget all goodneſs, and in a moment they go down to the Grave, and Rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs takes faſt hold upon them.</p>
                  <p>In a Word, for there is no end of writing Books upon ſuch Subjects, to informe and rebuke all men at all times, as they have need, for all their wild Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies: Let us hear all in a little. <hi>Fear God and keep his Commandments: keep Faith, and a good Conſcience:</hi> yet more briefly. <hi>Love is the fulfilling of all Gods Commandements.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:93356:49"/>
               <head>An <hi>APPENDIX</hi> for PEACE.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Tranſition. </seg>
                  </label> I Have in my former Diſcourſes endeavoured to ſatisfy and comfort weak, fearful,and melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirits, who though they have true Faith; yet by reaſon of their own Diſtempers within, and the Temptations without, complain for want of that Faith and Aſſurance which they have already.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It remains that I ſhould farther put on to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy, concerning Children that dye, before they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to Faith or the uſe of Reaſon, in what condition their ſouls are in.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As alſo concerning Innocents and Fools, that all their life long are ſuſpended from the uſe of Reaſon.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As alſo concerning Mad-men, who, after the Exerciſe of Reaſon, have been deprived thereof for ever; or have loſt it for a time, and then recovered it, and loſt it again.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As alſo of them that periſh by Fire or Water or dye ſuddenly by any other accident.</p>
               <p n="5">5. As alſo concerning them, that in their health of Body, enjoy health of mind: but when Sickneſſes have violently ſeized upon their Bodies, their Souls have loſt all ſober uſe of underſtanding, will, or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory to the outward appearance; only the Fancy
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:93356:50"/>abounds with abſurd <hi>Idaeas,</hi> and repreſentations of things never acted by them, or ſometimes by any other. And thence proceed expreſſions of Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, Uncleanneſs, Nonſenſe, to the great trouble and amazement of their weak friends, eſpecially if they chance never to recover their wits again.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And laſtly concerning thoſe honeſt Heathens that have excelled in virtue, and the fear of God; either upon the ſtock of natural knowledge and their own practice: or ſome farther ſecret Revelation that God hath made unto them, In what ſtate or condition their Souls may be thought to be in.</p>
               <p>And theſe are all the caſes of doubt that I can think on upon this preſent Subject.</p>
               <p>To theſe I ſhall ſtrive to give a modeſt anſwer with ſubmiſſion to better Judgments, being farr from a Magiſterial Spirit of abſolute Determination in any thing, ſave what God hath moſt cleerly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to all.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I ſay then as to the firſt Caſe of Infants that dye in that eſtate.<note place="margin">Chap. 1.</note> I think their ſouls are in a very ſafe condition.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                  </label> And the Reaſon is from Gods infinite juſtice as well as Grace. That though their Fathers have eaten ſown Grapes, yet they their childrens teeth ſhall not be ſet on edge. They muſt dye, becauſe they are the children of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> by Nature, that brought in death by his Sin, which is the wages thereof: But they ſhall not dye everlaſtingly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are the children of the Second <hi>Adam,</hi> by Grace that brought in life everlaſting; by his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs which is the Reward thereof.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:93356:50"/>
               <p>As for their actual non-ſtipulation, ſuch as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in ordinary Covenants, and in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, I ſuppoſe their incapacity which God puts them, in of ſuch Stipulation for want of Power to uſe Reaſon, ſhall not render them inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the Grace of God to excuſe them by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary favour, for what they could not help.</p>
               <p>For notwithſtanding the impoſſibility of actual acceptation of their Will; yet probably God may convey that Grace unto them, which he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to the faithful, and their Seed: though at preſent they do not know it, yet hereafter they ſhall know it, to their great admiration of that Grace, that brought them unto Glory.</p>
               <p>And what ſhould hinder them from being ſuſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible of the benefit of Gods Promiſes, although they underſtand not Faith. For are they not innocent? and will God condemn the innocent, as he doth the wicked? ſhall not the Judge of all the World do right? This be farre from God to judge unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judgment, and this be far from us to think of God after ſuch a faſhion.</p>
               <p>Are not Infants free from all love of the World, or malicious wilfulneſs to put by Grace, or to grieve the Spirit of God, whereby they are ſealed unto the day of their Redemption?</p>
               <p>And is it not an exuberancy of Love, and ſuch as becomes the God of Love, to help thoſe poor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that cannot help themſelves? And can he in Juſtice create ſuch innumerable and helpleſs Souls, and give them but a ſhort life, without all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:93356:51"/>or ſenſe of pleaſure, on purpoſe to damn them to everlaſting pain, and make them fuel for Hell-fire; only to ſhew what he can do! Certainly Gods thoughts are not like mans thoughts, ſo cruel; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are his wayes like mans wayes, ſo unjuſt: But they are of a better faſhion; neither may we think God to be ſuch a one as our ſelves.</p>
               <p>Secondly concerning Innocents and Fools,<note place="margin">Chap. 2.</note> that have lived long, and yet never attained to the uſe of a Rational Soul, I think theſe are more miſerable wretches then children that dyed in their Infancy; but not more ſinful: but both are alike innocent and harmleſs before God. That ſtained condition, that they, as Sons of Traitors are in by Law, that have forfeited their Eſtates, is a ſufficient puniſhment for this World, by Grace they are moſt certainly free from the puniſhment of the next World. For theſe poor Lambs what have they done? that never were in a capacity ſo much as to will good or bad. And 'tis a true ſaying; <hi>Nihil ardet in inferno, niſi propria voluntas.</hi> Nothing ſuffers in Hell, but the ſinful Will.</p>
               <p>What does Baptiſme conſign,<note place="margin">Chap. 3.</note> but an Ablution from Original Sin, and a Death to all Sin, and a life to Righteouſneſs, and thereby exemption from the ſtate of Damnation to the ſtate of Salvation; and that to Infants as well as others, that are Baptized with water: and if not Baptized it was none of their fault. And whither outwardly Baptized or no, what can hinder the Inward Baptiſme of the Spirit, to them if they Dye preſently before or after Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme;
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:93356:51"/>or to others, if they live long to believe and keep that Faith in which they were Baptized: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they make Shipwrack both of Faith and a good Conſcience, by breaking the Vow and Promiſe made by them.</p>
               <p>None can deny but the Spirit of God is free as the Wind, to blow where, and when, and how it liſteth; and who ſo fit objects to receive the gifts of his Grace for life Eternal, as theſe poor Creatures that are ſo miſerable, as not ſo much as to enjoy the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of this life Temporal? Do not Rights belong to Children and Fools by Law, but Grace gives Rights above and contrary to Law: Eſpecially the Grace of God, which is ſo Gracious, that our ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low underſtandings and ſtammering Tongues, are not able to apprehend and expreſs it.</p>
               <p>I will therefore ſtand ſtill, admire and hold my peace, when I cannot fathom his Infinite Mercy.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, Concerning Mad-men, who have had Reaſon and Faith,<note place="margin">Chap. 4. <hi>Untimely Ends.</hi>
                  </note> and afterwards without their own fault, have loſt the uſe of both; at leaſt <hi>Quoad nos,</hi> to outward appearance, either wholly, or for a certain time, or times coming and going, I am as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable to judge of them, as I did for Infants and Fools.</p>
               <p>I know well, God is favourable, and his Royal Laws moſt favourable, and to be moſt favourably interpreted (as good men will allow their own Laws to be) And therefore it becomes me and all men, to come as neer unto God for kindneſs as we may, and it is moſt ſafe ſo to do.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:93356:52"/>
               <p>I ſay then, as favourably as I can, thus: As they have had Reaſon and Faith before their diſtraction; ſo they have them ſtill under their Diſtraction. The Habits they retain, the Acts they cannot ſhew. It is all alike to God, though not to us. He knows what the Inward Man is; though we do not, but by the expreſſions of the Outward Man to gueſs only.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Fourthly,<note place="margin">Chap. 5. <hi>Untimely ends.</hi>
                  </note> Concerning ſuch as have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and faithful both, and fruitful in Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Goodneſs; and yet have ſuddenly perſhed by Fire, or Water, or the Sword, or any other fatal Contingency, I anſwer, I do not judge amiſs of their Souls at all for the grievous miſery that hath happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto them: No, not if they have in their Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or Provocation of uncharitable Cenſures, thruſt out their own Souls out of their Bodies, ſuppoſing they were ſuch as conſtantly feared God before.</p>
               <p>They have not loſt the life of their Souls, though they have loſt the life of their Bodies; they have not loſt an Eternal, though they have loſt a Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral life.</p>
               <p>All theſe Changes and Chances of a long Life or a ſhort, of a natural or violent Death, of a Single or a Married life, of Poverty or Riches, of Beauty or Deformity, of Ignorance or Learning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the farthering or hindering of the ſtate of a Bleſſed Eternity.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Fiftly,<note place="margin">Chap. 6. <hi>Sickmen di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted.</hi>
                  </note> Concerning them, that in their health of Body have enjoyed health of minde, with Faith and a good Conſcience; but afterwards have been diſtracted, by violent Diſeaſes and never recovered:
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:93356:52"/>But (as other Madmen, that walk abroad, or are ſhut up, as otherwiſe healthy and ſtrong) they do talk not only idly and fantaſtically, but wickedly and profanely, and act altogether ragingly.</p>
               <p>I am not afraid to anſwer, that notwithſtanding all theſe things have happened unto them through Gods Providence, againſt their own Wills; yet their Souls are in as good and as ſafe a condition, as ever they were before.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
                  </label> But what will you ſay (may ſome object) of them,<note place="margin">Chap. 7. <hi>Malefact<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rs.</hi>
                  </note> that for and by the guilt of ſome grievous Sins, as Murder, Rebellion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or for ſome grievous Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as Love, Want, loſs of Children, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have fallen Sick, and loſt their Wits withal, 'till they have dyed either by meer ſickneſs, or by laying violent hands upon themſelves?</p>
               <p>I anſwer, And what will you ſay, that make this objection, or what can any man ſay of theſe men whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they repented or no, between the Bridge and the Water? or of God, whither his wayes be not often ſecret, but alwayes juſt?</p>
               <p>And whither, think you, is ſafeſt, for me to ſay they are damned, or to hope the beſt; that by the favour of God, puniſhing them here, they may be ſpared hereafter?</p>
               <p>If you can give a better Judgment then I in this Caſe, then do. I leave them to that God that made them, who is infinitely juſt and good, and knows how to relieve the weak. And hope the beſt.</p>
               <p>'Tis dangerous to walk upon the Ridges of head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long and ſlippery Places, as the Tops of Towres and ſteep Rocks, or Brinks of deep Waters.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:93356:53"/>
               <p n="6">6. Sixthly and laſtly,<note place="margin">Chap. 9. <hi>Heathens.</hi>
                  </note> There is one Caſe more, and it is as much as I can think of, concerning thoſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Heathens, that have excelled in virtue, and the fear of God; though never Circumciſed to the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Law, nor Baptized to the Chriſtian Goſpel: but only for ought we know, have grown good upon the Stock of Natural Light, or ſome ſecret ſupernatural Illumination, in what ſtate or Condition their Souls may be thought to be in.</p>
               <p>I anſwer as well as I can. That their Creed is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that God is; and that he is a rewarder of all ſuch as diligently ſeek him. And ſo they came to God, and whither he rejected them after they came to him as well as they could, let the wiſe judge.</p>
               <p>If then they do believe that God was a Rewarder,<note place="margin">Chap. 9. <hi>Jewes.</hi>
                  </note> then there is no Reward but in Chriſt: And what did the Jewes know cleerly of Chriſt, or of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection; were they therefore damned? They had a dark Diſpenſation of Reſemblances of Heavenly things by the Patterns of Earthly Ceremonies and Promiſes, and theſe a darker, by natural light and impulſe. If Spiritual and Eternal things were gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally hinted unto them, and they walked according to what they knew, as the beſt Jews did; God will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>equire no more at the hands of the Jew or Gentile then what he hath given them. The one ſhall be judged by that Law they had in Tables, and the other by that Law they had in their hearts, and the Chriſtians by that Spiritual Law of the Goſpel, the Perfection of both the former.</p>
               <p>And God will have all men every where to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:93356:53"/>and in every Nation, and at all times, they that fear God and worſhip him, and do juſtly as well as they can, ſhall be accepted of him.</p>
               <p>And whatever their condition be, which yet we have no cauſe to judge damnable, they ſhall moſt certainly riſe up in Judgement againſt them, that know more and do leſs.</p>
               <p>Let me add now certain Reaſons applyable to the ſeveral Caſes of the Perſons before ſpecified.</p>
               <p>A former life well led in the uſe of Reaſon and Faith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap. 10.</hi> A good Life denominates Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> is ſufficient to denominate that Perſon Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that afterwards did fall into Frenzy, or into a Lethargy or Apoplexie, or any other ſtupifying, or diſtracting Diſeaſe to his dying houre, as alſo into a Pit, or into Fire or Water, or any other danger never to be eſcaped. Nor can the Principles and Seeds of Moral or Divine Virtues, be rooted out of the Soul by the violence or permanence of any bodily Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or by any ſudden deadly chance whatſoever.</p>
               <p>The Reaſon of this Reaſon may be, becauſe the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is but the Organ of the Soul, and that very weak and dull, whereby it may operate in this World; and therefore the indiſpoſition that is, is of the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment only, and not of the rational and ſanctified Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which is untouched all this while, and when the Body fails can work better without it, 'till it be Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualized, and fitted for the mind to act by for ever in the World to come.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Beſides, All Spirits of good men made perfect, or not made perfect, out of the Body, or in the Body; in this World, or in the World to come, have
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:93356:54"/>communion with God ſtill, and with the whole Church which is the Body of Chriſt the Head; and therefore ſafe with the Father of the Spirits of all fleſh before, in, and after all bodily diſcompoſures.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider farther, That a Diſeaſe may, and can kill the Body; ſo can Poyſon, a Sword, a Fly, and other accidents of all ſorts: But nothing can hurt or kill the Soul but Sin. Fear not therefore that that can kill the Body, and go no farther; but fear that that can deſtroy both Body and Soul in Hell-fire, which is living and dying in Sin, I ſay, Fear that.</p>
               <p>As for idle or profane Words or Actions,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap. 11.</hi> Idle Words or Actions.</note> ſpoken or done by children, fools, or madmen in Sickneſs, or out of Sickneſs, They ought not in the leaſt to be cenſured for them, as guilty of ſuch words or actions.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Becauſe when a Man falls into an eſtate or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition which he could not help, and in which he cannot deliberate, nor chooſe at all, Thoſe Words or Deeds that are ſpoken or done by him during that ſtate or condition, they are none of his.</p>
               <p>Therefore theſe miſerable Perſons are never cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by any Laws for ought they ſay or do,<note place="margin">Chap. 12. <hi>Cenſur. s.</hi>
                  </note> though never ſo irregular; Becauſe it is not in their Power to help this infirmity at all: and in the judgment of the Law, they have no will, becauſe they cannot uſe any. And they are already too miſerable from the hand of God, and that's Puniſhment enough to free them from the hands of Men.</p>
               <p>He that knows not what he ſayes or does, is next to him that is Innocent. They that cannot deliberate or chooſe, are neither good nor bad.</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:93356:54"/>
               <p>Ignorance involuntary and invincible, muſt needs excuſe; becauſe the Law ſayes, <hi>Errantis nulla volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, nullus Conſenſus,</hi> Ignorants have no Will, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent not, diſcerne not; therefore they are not Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, for none can ſin without, or againſt his Will, as none can do good without or againſt his Will.</p>
               <p>Thus Children born blind, dumb, deaf, lame, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> muſt not be upbraided for their miſery; for that is a reproach to their maker, cannot be upbraided for their ſin. Their tender Age preſerves their Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, they are yet white Paper, and cannot be ſulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the World, the Fleſh, or the Devil.</p>
               <p>In like manner any ſickneſs, or any other diſaſter that takes away the Wits, or the Life; and comes not by our fault (theſe things being out of our Power,) they keep the Innocent party from being polluted.</p>
               <p>When therefore ſuch poor Innocent Souls, are ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized by the hand of God, lying ſo ſore upon them as to bereave them of their Senſe or Life: alas! They are to be pityed, not condemned; for why, much evil have they ſuffered, but what evil have they done?</p>
               <p>What if they talk idly or filthily,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap. 13.</hi> Sleep and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</note> or rave and take on furiouſly? We well know, that in ſleep, when men are in their health and wits, the fancy is awake and very idle, which occaſions talking and doing agreeable to that idle fancy in them that dream, and talk, and walk in their ſleep.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe in Sickneſs and Diſtraction withall, the fancy is heigthened to ſtir more, then in Health and Sobriety, which occaſions words and deeds, both agreeable to ſuch a diſturbed fancy.</p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:93356:55"/>
               <p>Now if the Body be awake and not overcharged with wild vapours flying up into the Head, then the Soul can hinder the Tongue and Hand from expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or acting, as the toyiſh fancy did dictate in ſleep otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>And though a thouſand ridiculous and impertinent conceipts flutter about in my brain, yet my ſober un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding &amp; will, diſapproves and rejects them all, not owning them in the leaſt, if I be my own man; and ſo never ſuffering them to be uttered or performed.</p>
               <p>But when I am aſleep, or dream, or am ſtark mad; I know neither what I ſay, nor what I do; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all that I ſay or do then, is nothing to me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe none of mine.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap. 14.</hi> Innocence pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</note> Solus cùm te praeſtare poteſt</l>
                  <l>Furor inſontem, Proxima puris</l>
                  <l>Sors eſt Manibus, Neſcire nefas.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Since thy fury only makes the guilt leſs, thy condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is next to the pure Wights that know no evil.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Innocens ſi furere coeperit, aut innocens reſipiſcet, aut innocent morietur.</hi> If an innocent perſon grow mad; either when he returns to his Wits again, he ſhall be innocent as he was before: or if he dye di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted, he ſhall dye innocent as he lived innocently.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nulla Aetas, nulla Sanctitas, nulla Cuſtodia ſic, innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem conſervat, ut Furor. Qualem invenit, talem reddit.</hi> No Age, no-Mortification, no cloſe Cuſtody can ſo preſerve a mans innocency from being tainted, as doth diſtraction of the mind; for juſt as it found a man when it firſt took him, ſo ſhall it leave him.</p>
               <p>Infancy and Madneſs is without all Crime, which is the root of puniſhment.</p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:93356:55"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap. 15.</hi> Drunkenneſs and Paſſion.</note> As for Drunkards with Wine or Rage that ſpeak and act monſtrouſly and moſt illegally and irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, The Caſe is otherwiſe with them. They might have helped it. They have brought this condition upon themſelves. They ſhould not have looked upon the Wine when it was red and moved its ſelf aright by ſparkling in the Glaſs for the riches of the ſpirits thereof. It was in their power to have withſtood ſtrife and hatred at the firſt, before it came to the heighth of fury and revenge.</p>
               <p>They ſhould have conſidered Wine, and Love, and Malice, if not reſtrained by Prudence in time, inflame the heart with unruly Paſſions, and urge the Patient to Jealouſies, Railings, Fightings, which end in Wounds or Death.</p>
               <p>And therefore <hi>Pittacus</hi> ordained a double puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſuch as were drunk, and committed outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges during their drunkenneſs; one for their drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and another for the miſchiefs done by them. Drunkenneſs therefore is ſtyled <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. A Divel that we invite to come unto us, A Madneſs that we bring upon our ſelves.</p>
               <p>Callicles <hi>in the Comedy did well convince</hi> Dinar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus <hi>when he prayed for Pardon, ſaying,</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>—Quod animi impos vini vitio, fecerim.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Excuſe me, It was my Wine, not I, did this:</hi> Non placet in mutum quicquid conferri, quod loqui non poteſt.</l>
                  <l>Nam vinum ſi fabulari poſſit, ſe defenderet.</l>
                  <l>Non vinum moderari, ſed vino ſolent,</l>
                  <l>Qui quidem probi ſunt: verùm</l>
                  <l>Qui improbus eſt, ſive bibit, ſive idem caret Temeto;</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:93356:56"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tamen ab ingenio eſt improbus.</hi> That is, I like not your anſwer, That you ſhould lay the fault upon the wine, A dumb thing that cannot ſpeak for its ſelf; for if it could, it would defend its ſelf well enough. Blame not the Wine then, for Wine does not go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern a good man, but a good man governs the Wine: But he that is wicked is wicked from within, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he drinks or no.</p>
               <p>If you ask me concerning the Reaſons,<note place="margin">Chap. 16. <hi>Extraordinary Viſitations.</hi>
                  </note> why the above mentioned Perſons are ſo extraordinarily vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited. I anſwer, I cannot tell; for Reaſons are beſt known to God himſelf, and thoſe moſt juſt, though hid from us. Certainly they are plagued, not for their extraordinary Sins, nor yet of their Parents: but that God might ſhew his Glory, and make his mighty Works to be ſeen, and to humble us for our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation from ſuch grievous miſeries, for our Deſerts that we have. To render us thankful for his free Grace and Love, and to make us careful and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to offend, leaſt ſuch or worſe things come unto us.</p>
               <p>And that we ſhould not inſult over their woe, nor tread upon them that are down, and add ſorrow to their ſorrow: but rather fear and tremble at the mighty works of God, and repent for fear, we ſhould all likewiſe periſh.</p>
               <p>Learn therefore to pitythoſe harmleſs &amp; diſtreſſed Creatures.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap. 17.</hi> Pity and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</note> O pity them all you that are their friends! All you that are Chriſtians! yea, All that are men!</p>
               <p>Shake not your heads, and mock not, as the Jews mocked Chriſt upon the Croſs.</p>
               <p>Say not in the Pride and Error of your minds,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:93356:56"/>doubtleſs theſe Perſons were ſinners more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, or elſe God would never have ſo extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily afflicted them. <hi>Judge not that ye be not judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> Be not like unto <hi>Jobs</hi> friends, that becauſe God had deprived him of all worldly comforts, therefore they charged him to be an Hypocrite. Theſe were miſerable Comforters, Phyſitians of no value.</p>
               <p>Remember your Saviours words.—<hi>Think not that thoſe, whoſe bloud</hi> Pilate <hi>had mingled with their Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, or thoſe on whom the Tower of</hi> Siloam <hi>fell, were ſinners above all others that dwelt in</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>becauſe they ſuffered ſuch things: I tell you, nay; but except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi>—<hi>Rejoyce not againſt me, O mine enemy! for though I do fall, yet I ſhall riſe again.</hi> —<hi>They that go forth weeping, bearing good ſeed, ſhall doubtleſs come again rejoyeing, bringing their ſheaves with them. And greater ſhall their Reward be in heaven. Put on therefore (as the Elect of God holy and beloved) bowels of mercies, kindneſs, humbleneſs of mind; and above all things, put on Charity which is the band of all perfection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pity the condition of thoſe, whoſe Infancy, Youth, and Beauty are aſſaulted, with Conſumptions, Poxes, Lameneſs, Madneſs, and Death, which is the laſt Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; whoſe Prime and Golden yeers are cut off, and all their Wits and Parts turned into folly. Alas! the budding Tree, and the Tree laden with mature fruits, ſuddehty wither and dye. The faireſt flowers are cropt in their full glories. The Sun ſets at Noon day. And yet they are either altogether innocent as Infants; or ſetting humane infirmities aſide, more
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:93356:57"/>righteous then other men, and yet they are plagued more then other men. But do not you therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the generation of the Juſt; becauſe the hand of God is upon them. I ſay therefore, that except you have ſuckt the breaſts of Tygers, and partake of the nature of the ſavage Beaſts in the wilderneſs, you cannot but ſtop your uncharitable cenſures and leave them to that God that made them, and will ſave them, and look you to your ſelves.</p>
               <p>And now before I take off Pen from Paper, I think fit to add one word more for the uſe of this Doctrine delivered, which is; To take off all Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes, if it were poſſible, and that the minds of proud, contentious, and intereſſed men would bear it, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the great noiſe that is made of Infallibility, Supremacy; the Light that is in us maintained, either by the Pope, Presbyter, Independent or Quaker; as alſo thoſe endleſs wranglings of Schoolmen or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſts, which make up ſuch heaps of confuſed Volums to the diſtraction of Churches and States for <hi>Jews, Turks,</hi> and <hi>Heathens</hi> to laugh at.</p>
               <p>For if Faith be the ground of all Juſtification and Aſſurance,<note place="margin">Chap. 18. <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>dation.</hi>
                  </note> What need all thoſe heart burnings and ſeparations about the Notion of the True Church; Seeing all that hold the faith of Jeſus Chriſt, are the members of Chriſt all the World over, though they differ about Conſequences and Superſtructures, and forms of Diſcipline or external Worſhip. If any man ſhall build upon that precious Foundation, Gold or Silver, or precious Stons, Wood, Hay, Stubble; every
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:93356:57"/>mans work ſhall be made manifeſt.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.1.12, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>For the day ſhall declare it, becauſe it ſhall be revealed by fire, and the fire ſhall try every mans work of what ſort it is. If any mans work abide which he hath built thereupon, he ſhall receive a reward. If any mans work ſhall be burnt, he ſhall ſuffer loſs; but he himſelf ſhall be ſaved, yet ſo as by fire. And other foundation can no man lay, then that is layd, which if Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We all agree in the main Foundation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we might all hold the unity of the Spirit in the Band of Peace. Therefore all other unneceſſary Queſtions that engender nothing but ſtrife do vaniſh of themſelves, and it will be found ſufficient to hold to thoſe few things that are neceſſary for ſaving Faith and Life, and to trouble the people of God with no more Controverſies.</p>
               <p>Let all ſubtle, Factious and Seditious ſpirits, pack up their bundles of Traſh and be gon. We give them to underſtand, that we have no ſuch cuſtom, nor the Churches of God. We have enough to ſecure us for Heaven hereafter, and for Peace while we live here.</p>
               <p>Here is a ſafe and a ſhort way propounded for happineſs, if they will take it. From henceforth let theſe Dividers look to themſelves, and Teach no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the Scriptures for Doctrine, and the Laws of their ſeveral Countries for Diſcipline, and be quiet.</p>
               <p>I wiſh Councils would make no more Creeds nor Definitions and Canons, forced with deadly Curſes and Anathema's againſt all Diſſenters.</p>
               <p>I wiſh no one Church would dare to Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate another, nor the ſame Church cut off her own
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:93356:58"/>Members ſo deſperately, for ſome fond opinions, or ſcruples: for they do but ſhew their malice and pride, in calling Fire from Heaven in all haſte. Their blows cannot hurt a Soul that is ingrafted into Chriſt, nor cut off any from Communion with him or his People in the Spirit. They do but beat the aire. They know not what ſpirit they are of.</p>
               <p>Away with Tranſubſtantiation, Conſubſtantiation, Merits, and Works of Supererogation, Prayers to Saints or Angels, Indulgences, Purgatories, Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macies, Infallibilities, Pilgrimages, Whippings, Penan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or Pecuniary ſatisfactions, and ſuch like ſtuff.</p>
               <p>Theſe things are not worth the ſtriving for (they are all Hay, Straw, and Stubble) to the effuſion of Chriſtian blood, and waſting of Treaſures, How long will the World be deluded with vain Words! It is enough to contend for the Faith that was once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Saints; and neither to add to it, nor take from it, as it is contained in that Rule of Faith, the Creed Apoſtolical, out of Gods Word. And all Divines and others ſhould do well to bend their forces this way, againſt the common enemy.</p>
               <p>And pray what good have the Diſputes about ſuch things ever done?<note place="margin">Chap. 19. <hi>Diſputes.</hi>
                  </note> and what one Controverſy have they laid aſleep, or ever will, when both parties joyn wit to wit, fallacy to fallacy, equally triumphing, in their own ſtrength or ſucceſs; and neither party ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging themſelves foyled, but rather Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors.</p>
               <p>And in the mean time, while men contend for the Form of Godlineſs, the power thereof is loſt. They
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:93356:58"/>raiſe ſuch a thick duſt by ſtriving, that the Truth can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſeen; and while the ſtate of the queſtion is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating, The plain verity ſneaks away. The worſt is, they tye more knots, then they are ever able to unlooſe: and raiſe more Divels, then they are ever able to lay. This is the Scab of the Church, When <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and <hi>Plato,</hi> or an idle Legend, are grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Oracles, then the Scriptures themſelves.</p>
               <p>I would fain the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> would better conſider of theſe things, why they ſhould urge ſo many new Articles of Faith, and ſuch infinite Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh Ceremonies upon Chriſtians, and ſo hate, condemn, and perſecute to death the Reformed Party as they do.</p>
               <p>We are not ſo imperious and uncharitable to them, but hope favourably of the honeſt poor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under them, that are kept in ignorance, and muſt know no better. But woe be to the blind Guids!</p>
               <p>I would fain the Reformers of our Reformation would better conſider, what reaſon they have to ſtand off, and be ſo ſhy of the Epiſcopal and Royal Party; becauſe they do but their Duty to ſtand to the Diſcipline and Worſhip which by Law is eſtabliſhed.</p>
               <p>Lord what miſchief have theſe men done! Too like the old Zealots among the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Orators among the Gentiles. So they cauſe the People to hate the Prince, and the Prieſt, and raviſh their ſacred Rights, while they are pampered with the ſpoils of both, and of the people to boot.</p>
               <p>And the poor people on both, ſides will be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, becauſe naturally they do not love Dignities.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:93356:59"/>And this their Deceivers work upon.</p>
               <p>If they that have eyes would ſee, and they that have Ears would hear, and they that have hearts would underſtand, they would yeeld to the plain reaſon of Faith in the Laws of God, and to the plain reaſon of Law in the Statutes of men. But firſt, theſe ſweet tongued Orators muſt be removed. Theſe Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banks muſt be caſhiered. The Sea would be calme if the Winds were layd. If Princes would ſilence theſe Mimical ſtage Players, Nimble Sophiſters, and Fucous Declaimers, their Subjects would be wiſer and better then they are.</p>
               <p>If Kings take care in the firſt Place that God be ſerved after a pure and decent Form, preſcribed by their Law, they themſelves will be better ſerved.</p>
               <p>If Kings keep the Reins in their own hands, and never proſtitute their Sacred Rights to the ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Clergy and wild Rabble, they will do their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs; and keep the Church, Themſelves, and their Dominions in Peace.</p>
               <p>O bleſſed way if it could be taken! The only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to beget and maintaine Truth and Peace. Who but ſuch as are faithful to God and the King, can have any aſſurance of their Salvation?</p>
               <p>One thing more ſticks in the way: A Doctrine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcerned; hurtfull to Religion and Laws: I mean, An abſolute Perſonal Election and Reprobation.<note place="margin">Chap. 20. <hi>Decrees Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. A Diſhonour and Blaſphemy againſt the Good God, in making of him the Author of Sin and Miſery to moſt of his poor Creatures; ſo that they cannot love him as they would, that is ſo unjuſt and cruel to
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:93356:59"/>condemn them from all Eternity, for juſt nothing; and in time to make his Decree good, by forcing them to Sin, under a colour that they may be juſtly damned! I tremble to think, that <hi>Sejanus</hi>'s innocent Daughters muſt firſt be deflowred by the Hangman, that they might be capable to be put to death accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Law!</p>
               <p n="2">2. A Barre for ever, to any Satisfaction, Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance or Comfort to any Soul that is in Diſtreſs! A ſpade will be a Spade: The Black-moor cannot be made White; nor the Leopard looſe his Spots withal the waſhing in the world. They weary the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves in the very Fire. It is a Lottery, if a man have the luck of it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A gap it will be, do what they can, to all Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſs and Preſumption. If Elected, they muſt be called, and perſevere, let them take no care. If Reprobated, they are ſure to be damned, let them take never ſo much care.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A Proſtration and Enervation of all Laws and endeavours; There is neither Virtue nor Vice, to reward or puniſh, if the will be forced againſt its will to Good or Evil, as by a Fate it muſt be.</p>
               <p n="5">5. By it all Preaching and Exhortation to duty is a meer mocking. For God means not as he ſpeaks, Salvation to all; but he hath a ſecret reſerved Will of Damnation to moſt.</p>
               <p>Theſe and many more abſurd and profane conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, they can never avoid while the World ſtands, let them ſay or do what they pleaſe. But the thing that I wonder at is, That the people ſhould rather delight to hear theſe <hi>Boanerges</hi>'s, the Sons of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:93356:60"/>Thunder, then the <hi>Barnabas</hi>'s the Sons of Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But any thing will go down kindly from thoſe that ſpeak againſt the preſent Powers. For Power is a thing naturally hated, though it be Gods.</p>
               <p>But though they have the knack to cheat the Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and weak by the dril of their Clappers, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick faces, and demure deportment; Yet they cannot put out the Eyes of the Wiſe, that can diſcerne ſenſe from flams, nor ſtop the Ears of the prudent, that can diſtinguiſh betwixt the harmonious Touch of a skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Muſitian, and the harſh ſcrape of a Country Fidler.</p>
               <p>They know it can be no ſenſe nor honeſty, to bid men ſee that are born blind, to bid men run that are lame; or faſt chained, to bid men hear that have their Ears dammed up, To bid men eat and drink that are ſick, and can neither Taſt, nor take any thing; or if able to do both, ſhew them meat and drink, and ſnatch it from them.</p>
               <p>Though they may thus mock men, yet let them not think to mock God alſo: or that God is ſuch a one as themſelves: verily they have their Reward.</p>
               <p>See how great a part is deluded, if not ſtark mad.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Papiſts that Damn all out of their Church, as being without the pale, caſt overboord and ſunk.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The frantick Quaker ſays, of all other Sects, They are Damned. And both theſe look when God ſhall put the Sword into their hands, to deſtroy the Wicked, as the vermin of the World.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Zenonian Phariſaical</hi> Tribe, are of the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:93356:60"/>ſame ſpirit, but hide it more craftily. They are not for fire and faggot as the Papiſts, nor for a general Maſſacre, as the fift Monarchy men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But they are merciful to ſuffer the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> to live; only they muſt be hewers of Wood, and drawers of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to ſerve the Elect, which have the Right to all things. Good men and True, they can hunt down the game from his legs; and when the Dogs of the ſame pack ſtarted before them, and tore the game in pieces, they barked and howled ſadly, becauſe they loſt the benefit of the Prey.</p>
               <p>The Rabbies and Philoſophers began early to mingle their Extravagancies among Chriſtians: Next the Pride of Infallibility and Supremacy began to peep from the chief Seats of Empire, with Apiſh Imitation of Idolatrous Ceremonies. They had not learned yet throughly the Art of Defence, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing challenged by <hi>Arius</hi> and <hi>Pelagius</hi> thoſe Mighty Champions among the reſt, they came to cloſe Fights, and in heat of bloud let fly at random. Thus the Gap once opened, In ruſht a Crowd of Gow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Warriers, cutting down all opinions but their own, with the ſharp weapons of their Tongues and Pens, ſinging <hi>Jo Paean</hi> to this day, flatly determining by their Legiſlative Power againſt pure and modeſt Antiquity. And took occaſion ſtill by the very Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, ſtriving to be moſt contrary to them, from whom they did juſtly depart, taking all upon the credit of ſome few, who were moſt famous for ſtriking the firſt ſtroke.</p>
               <p>There was all along a moderate Party, eſpecial at
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:93356:61"/>this laſt overture: but they could not be heard for Peace, becauſe the Cry of the Zealots was againſt them, and ſo it is ſtill. But the heat of the buſineſs is in good part over: At leaſure the Diligent have better conſidered, and long for the Peace of Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endom.</p>
               <p>Young <hi>Dupradii Novices</hi> may be indulged to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve their Maſters, when they know no better; but when they come, for their time to be <hi>Lytae</hi> and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents themſelves, they may judge of what they have learned, and teach better. And ſo might thouſands do, if they knew their ſtrength and were not La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zy, and content with that little they have; and if they were not tyed up under preſent pains, or future Damnation, to believe all that is obtruded upon them: But the World we hope, will grow older and wiſer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:93356:61"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
